In the previous video we got introduced
to variables and we had a bit of
a play around with integer data types.
So now it's time to talk about different
types of data types and more information
about the integer data type.
So I'm going to close this first project
down by clicking on the red cross in the left
hand corner of the screen and I'm going to create
a new project.
I'm going to select Java and click on 'Next'.
I'm going to click on 'Create project from template'.
Click on 'Command Line App'.
Click on 'Next'.
I'm going to call this one 'ByteShortInt'.
And it will make sense as we go through the video,
why I'm doing that. I'm going to change the 'Base
package:' to com.timbuchalka.
But you can change that to literally at this
stage whatever you'd like. Click on 'Finish'.
Now firstly, I just want you to check a setting
before we go any further. I'm going to right-click
the 'project name' here, and them I'm going to go
down to where it says 'Open Module Settings'
and I'm going to select that.
Now you want to make sure that this 'Language level:'
is actually set to '8', which is 'JDK 8'.
In the previous section, we installed
the Java Development Kit version 8.
So we need to set that to '8'
to make sure we don't get an error
as we go through this video. Click on 'OK'.
Okay, I'm going to double-click 'Main.java' now
to make a bit more space, and I'm going to
start writing some code. If you remember
in the previous video we created
some code that did something like this:
'int myValue=10000'.
So what that was doing was creating
a variable called 'myValue' of type 'integer'
with a value '10000'.
So in computing terms the computer has
allocated enough space to store an integer
and it's assigned a name for that variable of 'myValue'.
But what actually is an 'integer'?
We know that it's a whole number,
but, what can we store in an 'integer'? Is it a
infinite number we can store in there?
So in actual fact, in computing terms
normally there's always a limit, as to what it
can do. There's a minimum and a maximum.
So with a data type 'int', the computer assigns
enough space to store a number that is
between the ranges of around about minus
2.147 billion to positive 2.147 billion.
So in other words a number that is in that range.
If we try and use a number that's
smaller than that range or greater than that range,
we'll actually get an error, and that's because it
physically won't fit in the space that
the computer has allocated.
In that scenario what you would use, is you'd use a
different data type, for that particular type of
processing that you want to do.
And I'll be talking more through this course
showing you which data types to use for the
particular scenarios. Generally speaking,
the 'integer' data type, I've introduced that to you first,
because that is the most common data type
and you'll normally use that. That'll be your
first variable if you're looking to
process something in whole numbers
you'd probably be using an 'int'.
But I want to show you some of the alternatives
and just go through so you understand
behind the scenes, the minimum/maximum
values that can be stored in this data type
as well as other data types.
So it turns out the minimum range,
I'm going to delete that and put 'myMinValue'
for an 'integer' is, I said minus two billion,
to it's '-2,147,483,648'.
So that is the smallest number that can fit in an 'integer'.
So we try and make it smaller still
if we make the 8 on the end a 9,
we actually get an error, and if we hover our mouse
'Integer number too large'
So all that sounds a bit funny, you'd think that
that probably should say 'Integer number too small', but
essentially what it's saying is, we've
trying to exceed the boundaries
of the minimum and maximum values of an integer.
I'm setting that back to the smallest acceptable number.
And, I'm just going to copy and paste this,
and we'll create a second variable with maximum value.
The maximum value is, by getting rid of the minus sign at the front,
that's the maximum number, 2,147,483,647.
So again if you try and make that larger,
we'll get the same error, 'Integer number too large'.
So I'll set that back to what it was.
So if you need to do whole number calculations,
an integer will only work if you've got numbers that are
inside that range. Now obviously for the
for the computer to store a number, that
large or that small, takes a certain amount of space.
Now just before I go on I want to make it clear
that any number that you type here that
you see is a fixed number that you're typing in
in a statement like this when you're defining a variable,
this part here to the right is called a 'literal'.
So we're typing in a literal there
to the right and that's a fixed number.
It wouldn't be a literal if you'd done something like
you created something like 'a*b'.
and you have those variables that existed in your project
that would not be a literal, that's an 'expression'.
But where you're typing in a number like that,
I just did an undo, that is a literal.
Now what you can do, is you can
change this. You can put underscores(_) in there
to make the number more readable.
Now this has been a feature that has come out since Java 7.
And that's why I asked you to have a look at
for the module settings when we went into that
earlier in the video, because this
could come up with an error unless you set
module change to test for Java 8.
So if you're typing in a literal,
you can use underscores. That makes the number
a lot more easy to read. So I suggest
when you've got a large literal number that you're
typing in like that you use underscores
to make it more readable.
So as I said the 'integer' is allocated a certain
amount of space by the computer.
Being efficient, if we want to do some
calculations and we don't want to use a number that's
within that range.
We want to use perhaps a much smaller number.
We can use a different data type.
And Java makes available to us
different data types for different types
things that we might want to calculate.
So the next data type I want to discuss
is called a 'byte'. So we can type this like:
'byte myByteValue = 10'
So what we're doing in there is we're telling the
computer is this is a data type of type 'byte',
and we're assigning the value of '10'.
And the name of course we're defining is
'myByteValue'. Now byte value is
is allocated by the computer a much
smaller amount of space, and consequently
can fit a much smaller number.
In actual fact a 'byte' can only store a number
in the range of -128 to 127. So literally,
that is the smallest number that will fit in a 'byte'
and the largest number that can fit is 127.
So if we try and exceed that, we get an error.
And likewise if we try and make the number
smaller than the amount of space
we get an error as well.
So why would we ever want to use a 'byte'?
A 'byte' is more efficient because it's
in round-about terms it would normally take
about a quarter of the amount of space of an 'integer'.
So if you've got a lot of calculations,
it can be far more efficient to use a 'byte'
because the computer is not allocating as much
space for a 'byte' than it is for an 'integer'.
And particularly in situations where
the computer doesn't have a lot of memory
or there's a particular type of java
program you're running, and particularly on
mobile devices for arguments sake
that haven't got a lot of memory,
it does make sense to use the right
data type for what you're trying to achieve.
So that's the 'byte. There's also another one,
which we call a 'short'. Now a 'short',
that value for a 'short', we'll put 'myShortValue'
for the name, and this can store a larger number.
Around 30000 for argument's sake.
But the actual largest number that can be
stored in a 'short' is -32768.
So if you try and go smaller, you get an error
and the largest is 32767,
and if we try to exceed it we get an error.
So again that's a different type
and generally speaking, a 'short'
is allocated about twice the amount of space
that a 'byte' is and about half the amount
of, that an 'integer' is.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to put a space there
and I'm going to put what's called a 'comment'.
I'm going to put two slashes (//) like that
and that defines a comment that we can just
type something in there that is for us
and that command is ignored by the computer.
So it's really great for documenting
and making sense of a program
to give yourself some notes that you
can refer to later. So what I'm going to do is
just outline what these variable types
are. So I'm going to put 'integer'
It's good to think of an 'integer' has a width of 32.
A 'byte', two slashes (//) again, byte
has a width of 8.
'short' has a width of 16.
Now generally speaking a 'byte'
is half the size of a 'short'.
In computing terms, in terms of how much space has
been allocated, and a short
is half the size of an 'integer'.
That's three data types that are all
based on 'whole' numbers. There is
one more data type and that's of use
where you've got a number that you want
to process that is larger than the amount for an 'int'.
and we call that a 'long'. We put:
'long myLongValue = 100'
Now technically that's wrong,
because when you're assigning a 'long' value,
you want to actually put the letter 'l' on the end of it.
and that tells the computer that this is a 'long'
value. You can put lowercase 'l' or uppercase 'L'.
I suggest you use an uppercase 'L' because that's
a little bit easier to read than the lowercase 'l'
sort of blends in and looks like a one (1).
So in other words that looks like a hundred
1001 if you don't look at it really carefully.
But if you put a capital 'L', you can see
clearly that's an 'L' and not a hundred.
And a 'long has a width of 64.
So what that means is it's double the width of an 'integer'.
And the actual number that we can store,
in the case of an integer, the minimum number was
2 to the power of 31.
But a 'long' value, we can actually store a huge number.
It's actually 2 to the power of 63.
So it's something like this, I'm going
to paste the number in. I can't actually tell you what
that number is but it's a huge number.
But that's the minimum, that's the smallest
possible number, and you can see there, it's got
18 numbers after the 9, so 19 numbers in total.
So, it's a huge value.
And the largest value is the positive version of that.
minus 1, so it would be like that.
So that's the largest possible number.
They are the four data types in Java
that deal with 'whole' numbers.
So when you're developing a program in Java,
you would be deciding when you're using whole numbers
as to which data type you'd be using
to solve your particular problem.
And as you work through this course,
you'll see a lot of these data types in action.
And you'll get more of an understanding as
to which one to choose for a particular scenario.
In general, as I mentioned,
you want to choose the 'integer' by default.
So probably 9 times out of 10,
or 8 times out of 10, you'd go up here
and you would choose your 'integer'
when you're dealing with 'whole' numbers.
Let's have a talk now about arithmetic
in the different data types.
In the previous video of course we did some
basic arithmetic using the 'integers'.
We can do something, just as a recap.
We can come up here and we can put:
'int myTotal = (myMinValue/2)'
It's /, the forward slash (/) is 'divided by'.
So that's just a simple bit of arithmetic
which takes the value of 'myMinValue'
which is -2,147,483,648 divided by 2.
No problems there. Now with the 'byte' value,
We can put:
'byte myNewByteValue = (myByteValue/2)'
Ahh, but we get an error.
Now why do we get an error?
Because the start seems to be okay but in the case of the 'integer'
we just defined it in brackets
to be myMinValue/2, but here we've got an error.
And if you have a look at the error that's coming up
on the screen it says 'Incompatible types
Required 'byte', Found 'int'.
So what it's saying is, well you're defining
a variable of type 'byte' so whatever you
type on the right hand side should be a 'byte'.
Should be of type 'byte', and
when we type in a number that fits
within the range of a 'byte' it accepts it
as you can see on the line.
The minimum value, we haven't exceeded
the value or we haven't exceeded the maximum
But when you type in an 'expression',
because remember something that isn't a fixed number
like in the case above. This is an 'expression'.
Whereas the one above is a 'literal',
because it's actually just a fixed number.
And what's happening here is this is the nature of
Java and what I was saying about how an 'integer'
is the sort of go to or the default
data type you should use for whole numbers.
By default, when you're making an assignment
in an expression, Java converts that to an 'integer'.
So what's happening here is, we're looking for a
type, looking for a value that's of type 'byte'
to put into our 'myNewByteValue'
variable which is type 'byte'. But Java has
converted that automatically to an 'integer'.
And therefore, it's now complaining
and saying, well I'm sorry but that's an 'integer',
and you're trying to fit an 'integer' into a 'byte'.
And we know that an 'integer' takes up a lot more
space than a 'byte', so that number physically won't
fit into the area of memory that has been assigned.
This is just a weird thing that Java does
and what you need to do to get around that
is you need to specifically say to Java, look
I want you to treat this as a 'byte'.
So to do that, we do something called 'casting'.
So we just put something in front of that, we just
put in, in brackets 'byte'.
So what we're saying is, Java I want you to treat
that as a 'byte', and Java gets rid of the error and says,
okay if that's what you want to do, I've converted...
I'm not going to make that an 'integer' any more,
that's now a type 'byte'. So therefore,
'myNewByteValue' which was a type 'byte'
has been assigned a 'byte' value
And we might just print some of these out just
so that we can see that we're on the right track here.
And when you put something like:
'myTotal =, this is a way to print the value
and print a bit of text there as well, plus
myTotal
and we'll put myNewByteValue
= myNewByteValue
Okay, let's 'Run' that. And as you can see,
looks like we got the right results here.
So that's correct. Likewise for a 'short'
you need to also do the same thing. So we can't
just put 'short myNewShortValue = (myShortValue/2)
As of course we get the same error.
And the error is 'Looking for a short' and found an 'int' again.
A similar error but this time it's the 'short'
So we fix this one by typing 'short'
Generally speaking, an integer is
the way to go and you can see that is the case
because Java by default if you don't specify the
type that you actually want it converts it to
an integer automatically and that's why I
would suggest that you always work
generally speaking with an 'integer' unless you've got
good reason to not do that. Okay,
so I'm going to delete that
and I'm now going to issue a challenge to you.
Now that I've deleted that off the screen,
So create a 'byte' variable
and set it to any valid 'byte' number, it doesn't matter.
Create a 'short' variable
and set it to any valid short number.
Create an 'int' variable and set it to any
valid 'int' number.
Lastly, create a variable of type 'long'
and make it equal to 50000
plus 10 times the sum of the 'byte'
plus the 'short' plus the 'integer' values.
Okay so pause the video here
and go away and do that and
when you get back I'll go through and show you how to do that.
PAUSE NOW - TRY TO SOLVE - THEN PRESS PLAY.
So how did it go, did you figure it out.
Well let's make a start on that.
So we'll do something like byte
we'll call it 'byteValue'
equals, we'll say it's '10'.
'short' that's our first variable
Our second variable 'shortValue'
equal '20' and 'int'
'intValue = 50'
So how are we going to do the next bit? Well
the next bit would be a 'long'.
We'll call this 'ourLongTotal'. So we'll put:
'ourLongTotal = 50000 +'
'10 *' (and it's actually a lot easier than you think, it's)
'(byteValue + shortValue + intValue)'
It was a little bit tricky in that you don't
need to enter the cast there
because this is converting automatically
to type 'long' and long will quite happily accept
an integer. To be more precise we could probably
put an 'L' there, 50000L + 10L *
the byteValue + the shortValue + the integerValue
you can print that out
longTotal, and if you 'Run' that now,
We get a total of 50800
and that's because it's 10 + 20 + 50 that's 80
So it's 50000 + (10 * 80) is 800, so that's 50800.
So a little bit of a tricky one there in that you
didn't need to do a cast there,
and the point I wanted to make there
is with variables of type
long or integer, you really don't need to
do any casting like you do for shorts and bytes.
If you put a value in a bracket
for byte or short, it will automatically be
converted to an integer, and a variable of
type long will also accept an integer value.
But of course just finishing off, if we wanted to do this
to a short variable, we going to put 'shortTotal'
We might say it's 1000 + 10 *  and we put
our byteValue, shortValue + intValue
We're going to get an error there
and what we do is we put the 'short' here.
So everything we want to deal with there is going
be of type 'short' and we then have
to put another bracket there
to make that a valid line. So
basically saying, everything in this bracket
is to be converted to a short.
So you can see that Java makes you
do a little bit more work when you're dealing with
variables of type 'byte' or 'short'.
And the point I want to make is that using
integer is the best one to use generally.
But even if you are using type 'long',
Java handles a lot of the complexity for you
and you don't have to do this casting.
Because a 'long' will happily accept
an 'integer' when you're defining a value
total as well. And just to confirm before we finish
if we printout 'shortTotal',
shortTotal, shortTotal, we'll 'Run' that.
'shortTotal' was 1800 and of course it was
a 1000 + 10 * 80 which was the sum of those three
10 * 80 is 800 the total was 1800.
So that's 'bytes', 'shorts', 'integers' and 'longs.
In the next video we're going to go ahead
and start talking about decimal numbers.
Because of course to date we've only
dealt with whole numbers.
But there are scenarios where you want to actually
go ahead and use decimal points.
For example converting pounds
to kilograms or something of that nature, where you
want to deal with decimal numbers.
So we'll go ahead and work on that
in the next video.