In the previous video we talked exclusively
about 'whole' numbers. Numbers that don't have
any decimal points.
But how do we actually deal with
floating point numbers?
So in other words, if we want to use one or more
decimal points.
Well in this video we're going to make a start
on figuring out how to do that in Java.
So I'm going to create a new project in 'IntelliJ'.
Select 'Java' as we normally do.
And I'm going to 'Create [my] project
from [a] template -> Command Line App,
and I'm going to call this one:
'FloatAndDouble'
I'm going to set the '[Base] package:' name again
We will be talking about the 'Base package:'
and what this means a little bit later.
For now you can set that to whatever you like.
I'm going to click 'Finish'.
Okay! So how do we go about dealing with
'floating point' numbers in Java?
So that is numbers that have got a decimal point (.).
So there's two data types in Java
to deal with 'floating point' numbers.
And they are called the 'float' and the 'double'.
And the 'float' is a 'single' precision,
and 'double' is 'double' precision
unsurprisingly, given the name.
So essentially, the 'double' data type has got
twice as much detail as the 'float'.
Let's start with an example.
I'm going to type some code in just so we can compare
what a 'floating point' number does compared
to a 'whole' number. So I'm going to create
an 'integer' variable type, call it 'myIntValue'
and I'm going to set that to the value of '5'.
Then I'm going to create a 'float'
And to do a 'float' you type in 'float'
and we'll call it 'myFloatValue = 5'.
Now you can do that, but the proper practice
for entering a 'float' is to enter an 'f'.
Put an 'f' after the number.
Whatever the number is, you put an 'f'
at the end to denote it is a 'float' value.
And because it is a 'single' precision number,
we can put a decimal point. So we could say
5.25 for arguments sake.
Because a 'float' actually handles that
prevision for us automatically.
But we're going to leave it as '5' for now.
And let's create a 'double'.
And we'll call the 'double', 'myDoubleValue = 5'.
So we'll do the same for that.
And we can put a 'd' which is the
proper way of defining a 'double'.
Putting a 'd' to signify
but the other thing we can do is we can put the
decimal point like so
5.25 and Java will automatically assume
that the number you entered with the decimal point
is a double. And this is
very similar to what I showed you in the previous
video where in an 'expression',
the right hand side of an 'expression'
Java would assume the number is an 'integer'.
In this case with a number with a decimal point,
Java will assume it's a 'double'.
So, we'll go back and set that to '5d' again.
So for example, I can't go back and do this,
'5.4', because Java's saying, required a float
and  [it's] found a double
Thinking back to the previous lesson,
so here's a quick challenge for you.
Thinking back to the previous lesson on how we used
the 'cast' to convert a 'byte' and a 'short',
How do you think you'd go about converting this
value here, '5.4' to a 'float'?
Go ahead and pause the video and see if you can figure it out.
and come back when you've finished and we'll go
and I'll show you what the answer is.
PAUSE NOW - TRY TO SOLVE - THEN PRESS PLAY.
So how did it go with the challenge? Did you figure it out?
Well the 'cast' if you want to force the value
would be the word 'float' in brackets
much like we used 'byte' and 'short'
in the previous video. But I wouldn't generally
recommend that. It would be far better
normally, to put an 'f' on the end like so.
Because it's a little bit clearer in the code,
and that's what you want.
But that is how you do it if you wanted to do it.
But anyway, I'll change that back so that's also '5f'.
So we've got three values now, 'integer', a 'float'
and a 'double', and they are all equal to '5'.
So let's go ahead and write some code. I'm going to
print something out for each of them.
So I'm going to type the abbreviation 'sout' and press 'Tab'.
And that creates that for us. Saves us typing a bit.
And we're going to put:
' "myIntValue = " + myIntValue '
I need to type 'sout' again, and put:
' "myFloatValue = " + myFloatValue ' and
[enter 'sout' press 'Tab' again]
' "myDoubleValue = " + myDoubleValue '
So probably won't be surprised when we 'Run' this
to what the result we'll get.
Now just double click that.
And we'll 'Run' it again.
And you can see here to the right hand side
the values. The 'integer' value was '5',
but notice how the 'float' value and the 'double'
value have a '.0' on the end of it.
So it's actually stored it as '5.0'
and that's because it's a 'floating point' number.
So that's all well and good. But what
do you think would happen if we change this
and put '5 / 2'?
So let's just run the first one,
just to see what the 'integer' value will come back as,
bearing in mind that it is a 'whole' number.
So you can see what's happened there,
we've tried to divide a 'whole' number, '5'
by '2', and the answer is '2'.
And that's because it hasn't taken into account
the remainder. It literally just said,
'2' goes into '5' only '2' times.
So we're not handling any reminder in that case.
But let's go back and do the same thing,
and we'll divide the second value by '2f'.
So, divide the floating point value of '5'
by the floating point value of '2f'.
And likewise for the double,
we're going to divide that by '2d'.
So let's just see what gets returned when we do that.
So that should hopefully now clarify
the difference with the data types. You can see that
'float' and the 'double' both give you the exact
value. In this case '2.5'
And because the 'integer' value is a 'whole' number
it's not retaining any remainders
whereas the 'float' and the 'double' is giving us
the complete answer, the correct answer.
And just to be sure that that is working we could
divide that by, let's just divide that by '3'.
And 'Run' that again.
You can actually see, the first one, 'integer'
that was only '3' goes into '5' once, so it returned '1'.
So 'float' has seven decimal digits of precision.
So that's numbers after the decimal point.
And a 'double' in fact has sixteen digits of
precision after the decimal point.
So you can see that the 'double' value is far more
precise. It also has to show you
before the default value for a decimal point
specify the 'f' or the 'd' is actually a double.
And that's another hint from Java
that it recommends that we use doubles.
So in terms of space, a 'float', you remember we
talked about this in the previous video
the width of an 'integer' is '32'
which is effectively 4 bytes. A 'float'
has got a width of '32' as well.
Which is equivalent to 4 bytes.
Can you guess what the 'double' will be?
The width of a 'double' equals '64'
which takes up 8 bytes.
So a 'double' takes up twice the amount
of memory than a 'float' does
But with that said there's still
really compelling reasons to use a 'double'
whenever you're using a 'floating point' number in Java.
First reason is that double precision
which is the use of a 'double' data type
is actually faster on many modern computers.
And secondly, many in-built functions in Java
math functions like 'sin' and 'cos' and so forth
they actually use doubles as their calculations
and you can understand why they'd want to do that
because it's more precise there's more
digits of precision. So that's really three
reasons why you'd want to use it.
And the fact that the 'double' is
actually faster on modern computers
Also the in-built functions in Java
usually use a 'double' and thirdly,
the 'double' is far more precise
So it's actually as you can see there
sixteen units of precision compared to just seven.
For that reason I recommend using 'doubles'
and from this point on in the course, I'm only
going to be using 'doubles' for mathematical
calculations. So it's now time
for another challenge.
So the challenge is as follows:
So here's the challenge:
Convert a given number of pounds to kilograms.
So the steps to take will be to create a variable
to store the number of pounds.
Secondly you need to calculate the number of kilograms
for the number entered above [pounds].
And you need to store that in another variable.
Thirdly, then print out the result.
using the 'System.out.println()'.
And there's a note there that should help you a lot
to figure out the conversion.
1 pound is equal to 0.45359237 kilograms.
So go ahead and try that now. Pause the video
See if you can figure that out.
Come back when your finished, and
start the video again and I'll show you my solution.
PAUSE NOW - TRY TO SOLVE - THEN PRESS PLAY.
So how did it go, did you figure it out?
Let's make a start on it.
So with Step 1, we need to create
a variable to store the number of pounds.
I'm going to call that:
' double numPounds '
And I'm going to make that ' = 200d '
' 200d ' So it's 200 pounds.
Next, we need to calculate the number of
kilograms for the number of pounds.
In this case '200' and store it in a variable.
So we're going to do another one, we're going to put:
' double (we'll call it) convertedKilograms = '
So our hint is that 1 pound = 0.45359237 kilogram.
So how do we go about that?
Well it's actually pretty straight forward,
all we need to do is multiply the number of pounds
by 0.45359237. Now you want to put a
'd' on the end there just again to tell Java that
this is a 'double' even though it would default
to it anyway, but just to be clear.
So we've now got our converted kilograms
then we do a sysout (sout)
' "Kilograms = " + convertedKilograms '
So now if we 'Run' that.
You can see that the kilograms is 90.718474
So let's check that now with Google.
So we can easily do that. So we can go to Google
And that will actually tell us the answer.
So 200 pounds is 90.7185. I'll just take a copy of that,
If you go back to 'IntelliJ',
And that was the result.
90.7185 and in our case it's 90.7184, but
847, so rounded up would be be 90.7185.
So therefore our calculation is correct.
So that's how you go about converting
pounds to kilograms.
And that in a nutshell is the 'float' and the 'double'
for dealing with single and double precision numbers
in Java. And just one last thing now just
to finish off. You remember in the previous
video we were able to use underscores
when defining a literal value.
So a literal value for a 'float' or a 'double' can be
done the same way. So we could for example put
' double pi = (now we could put) 3.1415927 ' (like so.)
Or with a 'd' to make it precise.
but we could also put, if we wanted too:
'141_' so you could put numbers
define numbers like that with underscores
if you wanted too to make it clearer or
you can of course also put them before the decimal point.
For example, 3_000_000.
So in that case the pi would be incorrectly
specified as 3000000.1415927d
So I just wanted to make the point that you can use
underscores to make your variables cleaner
when you are setting about it as a literal.
So that's it. We're now done with 'floats and 'doubles'.
In the next video we're going to have a look at
two other data types. Namely the 'char'
and the 'boolean. I'll see you in that video.