In the previous video we dealt
with single and double precision numbers.
In other words dealing with 'floating point' numbers.
In this video we're going to talk about
two additional data types.
The 'char' and also the 'boolean'.
So, let's make a start.
So I'm going to create a new project
I'm going to click on 'Java' as I've done in the last
few videos now.
'Create project...' make sure 'Command Line App.' is selected.
I'm going to call this 'Char' [C-H-A-R] AndBoolean
B double-O L E A N.
Company name (Base package) we're going to make that com.timbuchalka again.
com.timbulchalka, but you can make that
whatever you want. Click on 'Finish'.
And I'll just double-click that to make it more
space and let's get started.
So the two other data types we're going to
talk about in this video are 'char' and 'boolean'.
So firstly, 'char'. You define it as
myChar = and you can put a single quote (') there
and a number or a letter, like so.
That's what I mean, it can literally store one letter or one character.
You can open also a lower case number letter,
you can also mark it as a number
and you can even make it a special character.
Ampersands (&) and so on.
What you can't do is make it more than one.
So we can't put two numbers in there because we'll get an error.
And the error is 'Too many characters in character literal.'
So it literally can only be on character and
it's actually a width of 16. So it's actually 2 bytes.
So that's the standard characters that I'll be typing in there.
But you can also put what's called 'Unicode' characters.
And they are special characters that support multiple languages.
Just to show this to you, I've got a website
I'm just going to go to you know to Google chrome
I'm going to go to a website called 'Unicode-table.com'
And you can see I've just got
'/en'#control-character' on the end.
This gives a list of what's called Unicode
characters. So Java also let's us assign
a variable of data type 'char'
using a special code that I'm going to
show you how to do, so you can notice that
the Unicode table has got our regular
numbers and letters and so forth and special
characters like the percent (%) sign, the dollar ($) sign.
But as we scroll down, they've got lots of other
characters as well.
For example a copyright (©) symbol
and all these other accented letters
and the list goes on. There's quite a few of them.
So we could choose one, and what we need to do
to choose one, we need to start
to the left hand side
So let's just assume we want to
use the copyright (©) character. So we
start with '00A' then we move over to the character
move over to the table element position
in this case '9'. So we'll enter that
the value we need is '00A9'. So it's
starting on row '00A'. Moving right across
to '9'. So '00A9' is the code that we need.
And if we go back to Java,
what we can do is, we can put
a back slash (\), has to go that way
then we put a lower case 'u'
then we can type '00A' in upper case '9'.
Now that's what's called a 'Unicode' character.
So if we now do a print out,
Let's 'Run' that.
And you can see that the character has
been outputted as a 'copyright (©) symbol.
So the actual range of a 'char'
'char' is a width of 16.
Width of 16 which is effectively
two bytes. So that is the amount
that has been allocated for a 'char'.
Second type is called a 'boolean'.
So to use that we type in 'boolean'
'B' 'double-O' 'L E A N'.
'myBoolean ='
and there can only be two values.
The two values are 'true' or 'false'.
That's it! You can't have any other
value for a 'boolean'. And it's used
to test whether something is 'true' or 'false'. So,
it's really good for that. And you'll see that a 'boolean'
boolean's are very popular and used a lot
for conditional logic which we'll be talking about in future videos.
Probably the way you'd use a 'boolean'
you'd do something like:
'boolean isMale = true;'
The variable name is asking a question.
and the value will be whatever the answer's
set to. So this case we're saying is it a male?
as the variable name,
and we've assigned the value of 'true'.
But we'll be talking more about those in detail
in a future video.
So it's challenge time again.
So the challenge for this video is to find the code for the 'registered' (®) symbol
on the same line as the copyright (©) symbol on the webpage that I've shown you.
And incidentally, that website
is in the resources section of the video. So you can click over into the resources section
to find that link, or I'm going to go back and show you that on the page now if you want to write it down.
So you need to find the code for the 'registered' (®) symbol
and that's the symbol that is very much like a copyright (©) with a 'c' in the middle, but has an 'r' (®).
You then need to create a variable of type 'char' and assign it the 'Unicode' value for that symbol
and then display it on the screen.
So follow the three steps as I've shown on the screen
find the code, create a new variable
variable of type 'char' and assign it the 'Unicode' value for that 'registered' (®) symbol
then display it on the screen.
Okay pause the video, do that, come back when you're ready and I'll show you my solution.
PAUSE VIDEO NOW - TRY TO SOLVE - PRESS PLAY
So how did it go, did you manage to figure it out?
Well the code, going back to the browser first,
We start off on '00A'
and in this case the 'r' matches up with the 'E'
So we've got to put an 'E' on the end.
So where we used a '9' for the copyright (©) symbol,
We'll come over here
and it's an 'E', and did you notice that,
I didn't show you that before, but if you actually
hover over there it actually gives you
the code '00AE' as you can see.
So our code is going to be '00AE'
so go back to our code
We're going to put 'char registeredSymbol = '
'\u00AE;' on the end
And just to print it out, "Registered symbol = "
'registeredSymbol'
And that's it! That's he solution so we'll 'Run' that just to confirm.
And you can see we've now got a 'registered' (®) symbol
which is below the copyright (©) symbol which of course is
still printing above that. So that's it for the
'char' and the 'boolean' types.
In the next video we're just going to have a bit of a recap
on the eight (8) data types that we've covered to date.
They were called 'primitive' types and I'll just be
explaining what that means and then we're going to move on
to another data type a special data type
we're going to be looking at
that and that's called 'string'
and we're also going to be looking at that
in the next video.