In the previous video we looked at the
'char' and also the 'boolean' data type,
which was the 7th and 8th data types that we've
covered so far in the course.
It's now time to have a bit of recap of where we're at
with those data types.
And to also discuss a very important ninth
data type, that you're probably going to be working with
quite a bit in your Java programming.
So the eight data types that we've covered to date
are as follows, in order:
So we have 'byte', 'short', 'int', 'long', 'float',
'double', 'char' and 'boolean'.
So these eight data types, they're actually what's called
'primitive types' in Java.
Now when I say 'primitive' type, that's actually
something that's defined by the Java language
and is named by special reserved keyword
as you've seen. For example, the keyword
'byte - short - int - long' and so on and so forth.
So each of the 'primitive' types as you've found out
as you've seen has it's own style and is used
for different purposes.
The 'byte' as we found out can only hold
a number in the range of -128
to +127.
And as another example, the 'boolean' can be
'true' or 'false' only.
As you get more experienced in Java,
you'll learn to use the right 'primitive' type
data type for a given computing
problem. And that's actually all part of
becoming a programmer.
And I'm going to be teaching that as we go through this course.
So again just to re-enforce, those eight
data types we've looked at are 'primitive' types
in Java, and are built-in to the language.
As we go further through the course, you'll find
there's a way to create your own data types
also known as 'objects'. The interesting thing about
doing that in the future is you can actually
combine data types. For example,
if you create sort of like a 'super' data type,
that contains maybe a 'byte' and 'int'eger and a 'double'.
But we're going to be talking more about that in the future
because we're going to be getting into the concepts of creating
classes, and that's actually an entire
section of the course in it's own right, just to do that.
For now it's enough to know that these are the eight
basic types that are built-in to Java;
and that there is the ability for you to create your own
as we go further into the course.
Now just to be clear before we continue any further,
I did create a new project. You can see on the
screen, it's called 'Strings'.
We've created a number of projects
each time, so I'm going to assume you're pretty
familiar now with the process of creating a new project.
So just call it 'Strings', and the package
as normal can be whatever you like.
So they are the eight 'primitive' types
built into Java. But there is actually a
special ninth type, that whilst you can't say that it's a
'primitive' type. It's actually
something that's going to be used so commonly,
and it's been so integrated into the language
it really comes across as a ninth data type.
So I'm talking about something called a 'String'.
So firstly, what is a String?
Well a 'String' is a sequence of characters.
In the case of the 'char' which you saw,
that could contain just one character
and the 'char' could also contain
a 'Unicode' character as we showed.
Well a 'String' can contain a sequence of characters, so
any number, a much larger number of characters
than the 'char' which of course is limited to one.
So to define one, it's a simple case.
Just type 'String myString = "This is a string"'
So we're using double quotes this time. Remember with a
'char' we used a single quote around the
character we wanted. In this case with a 'String'
we use the double quote around the sequence of
characters that we want to represent as a string.
And just to ensure that that's printing out,
we can actually just print it out to the console
'myString', like so.
And incidentally, another way of running it
if you don't want to right-click all the time like I've
been doing. You can just come up here and
click on the 'green arrow' and that will 'Run' it as well.
And I'll just pull that over a little bit so there's a bit more
space there, we can see things a bit more clearly.
And you can see that 'myString is equal to This is a string'.
But we can also append to that string automatically,
by using the 'plus' operator.
So what we can do is we can put something like
myString = myString + ", and this is more.";
So what that's doing here, that's going to
append this text in this double quote
to what 'myString' really is. So what we're saying is
make 'myString' equal to
Whatever it currently is,
when the program gets to this point
So 'myString' is currently set
to 'This is a string' and then plus
to add this text on the end of it. So sort of to
append it to the string.
And if we just do a copy and we'll print that out again.
And we'll 'Run' it again.
You can see the first time, it's still showing the first
print output which is 'myString is equal to This is a string'.
The second time it's 'myString is equal to This is a string,
and this is more.' So it's added that to the end of the String.
So there are other ways to
add two strings. To put something like 'myString'
'= myString + " [we'll put a space there] \u00A9 [2015]"
You remember that from the previous video
that was the copyright (©) sign, it should be.
So if we do that, and do another print.
We'll 'Run' that!
'myString is equal to This is a string, and this is more.'
([full stop (period[.]) and the copyright (©) symbol as you
can see there '2015'.
So that's just appended at
using 'Unicode' characters. So you can do that as well.
But let's try something different.
Let's type a new string. We'll create a new
String called 'numberString'
and we can put a number in the double quotes.
And what we're going to do is add something
to it. numberString = numberString +
'49.95'.
So my question to you is 'What will happen there?'
Will this automatically, because they're numbers
Will that up and say 250.55 + 49.95
That would equal 300.00 normally if my math is correct.
So what will happen in this scenario if we go to
print this out?
"The result is " + numberString
So what's going to happen to that? Do you think the answer's going to be 300?
Let's 'Run' it and just see what the answer is, what it comes back with.
And can you see up here what it's done?
So it's taken the first value
250.55 and it's looked at the next bit and added
49.95 on it. However, it hasn't treated
it like a number, it's treated it as text only.
So it hasn't done any calculations on it.
And the reason it hasn't done any
calculations is we haven't used a data type
that supports numeric operations.
In other words we haven't used one of the primitive
types like a 'short', 'integer', a 'float', 'double' and so on
that actually allows you to
add numbers together. In this case,
because we specified the data type to be a 'String',
we are dealing with textual data only
and we're not dealing with anything
of a numeric capability.
So in other words it won't do those numeric
calculations. Later in the course I'll
show you how you can convert
what you think is a number from a String to a Number.
But as far as the default operations for a 'String' are,
it's going to treat something as a String every time.
So let's now look at another example.
'String [and we'll call this one] lastString = ""'
And here's another example. And let's actually
create an 'int[eger]' myInt =  [I'll make that] 50;
So what do you think is going to happen if we
put lastString = lastString + myInt?
Well it turns out that's valid Java code,
because we haven't got an error there.
So something has happened.
So what do you think is going to happen when we go to print this out?
Let's 'Run' it and see what it comes back with.
So what's happened there is we had 'lastString'
was initially set to '10'
integer which is a number was set to '50'
but in this line here where we've added
myInt[eger] to the 'String'
Because we're using a 'String' on the left hand side,
and there's an integer on the right hand side,
so what's happened here us we've
started off with a 'String'.
We've defined a 'String' and we know that the 'String'
isn't manipulated like a number in any way shape or form.
It can be alpha-numeric, it can be letters or numbers
or Unicode characters or whatever.
So it isn't treated like a number.
But then if we go and try to add a number to that,
Java is actually smart enough to say,
Okay, I note the 'int' you've defined as 'myInt'
is an 'integer' but I also know that you're trying to
add it to a string. So what Java does
it actually converts or effectively looks at
the contents of myInt[eger] and converts that into a 'String'
to add to the end. So you can see
what happened was, it appended
the number '50' to the end of the
first part which was the number '10'
So consequently, we've got still a 'String'
that just happens to contain the numbers 1050.
But it isn't a number in the true sense
it's treated purely as text by the computer.
And that holds true for other data types as
well. So we can do a 'double'
'doubleNumber = 120.47'
and we can put 'lastString =
'lastString + doubleNumber'
And print out
You can probably guess what's going to happen here.
Let's 'Run' it and see.
And as expected, it added
this bit here, the 120.47
again it converted to text
and got added into the 'String' as text.
Now this is only a very elementary way of
dealing with 'Strings' and adding to 'Strings'
In later lessons, we're going to go through
this and look at some of the more advanced
features of a 'String', because we can do all sorts
of things. We can delete characters out of it.
We can append characters which you've seen.
We can insert characters at specific
positions. There's lots of flexibility with 'Strings'.
But we need to know a little bit more about 'classes'
before we can get into that in too much detail.
Just want to make it clear that what I'm showing you today,
is plus something along these lines
you wouldn't normally do something like that in your
programming. You'd use other functions
to make it a bit more clear what you're trying to achieve.
By this stage we just wanted an introduction to this
'String' class, and that's where we've started, and just
to make that a little bit clearer, we know that the
eight (8) data types that we've explored
prior to the 'String' were 'primitive' types.
The ninth one, even though it looks
looks like it's the same, it's got its own keyword
and it's got an assignment and it's got
literal you can add to the right hand side,
It's actually not a 'primitive' type, it's actually
called a 'class' and it's treated differently.
But the Java syntax for this have made it
easy for us to use a 'String' class.
So from your point of view you'll be able to
treat it more or less as a ninth 'primitive' type.
So the bottom line here is, 'Strings'
are extremely powerful and we're going to
be using a lot of 'Strings' as we progress
through the course.
That's it! So hopefully, you've got a good
understanding of what a 'primitive' type is.
You now understand what the 'String' class,
and how even though it's not a 'primitive' type
you can more or less treat it as one
when you're using one.
So, in the next video we're going to start
talking about 'Operators'.
Now you've already seen some 'Operators', but
perhaps you didn't realize that's what they're called.
'Operators' are these things here.
And some of the 'Operators' you've already seen are the plus (+),
divided by (/), multiplication (*).
That's just a couple you've seen, so
and they actually deal with 'primitive' types.
And as you saw with the 'String' class,
and they're used much as you think they would be used
with for example as in the case of a
'long' we can use the plus (+) operator
to add two 'long' values together.
We're going to go through, because there's also some
extra 'Operators' that perhaps you're not aware of;
but we'll be talking more about 'Operators' in detail
in the next lesson.