In the previous video we had a discussion about
'primitive' types and also introduced the 'String' class.
In this video I want to start talking about what
'operators' are, so you can get a good understanding of
what they are and how to use them in your code.
For this video, I've created a new
project and I've called it 'Operators'.
So 'Operators' are actually special symbols that
perform specific operations on one,
two, or three operands, and then return a result.
Now you've actually seen this in use.
We've actually used a number of 'operators' already.
But now I just want to go through and clarify and
go through all the major 'operators' so you're very
familiar with them and know how to use them.
Now some 'operators' tend to appear in your
code a lot more frequently that others.
And as we start typing our code,
I'll show you the one that's probably the most
common one for you.
So you've seen this sort of code before:
'int result = 'something'.
We can do 'something' like '1 + 2'.
And that is using, there's two 'operators' there,
equal (=) and then also a plus (+).
That's an 'operator', and it's actually saying,
Whatever is evaluated on the right
hand side here, to place that 'value'
in 'result. So in this case,
'1 + 2 = 3' so therefore the value '3' would
be assigned by the 'equals' sign (=)
to the 'variable' called 'result'.
So you've seen something similar in the past
when I did something like this:
I'll just comment that out with the two
backslashes (\\) as we've seen before.
So that's using a 'literal' value there
of the number '1' to assign it to 'result'
So that's still using the equals (=) 'operator'.
But we're not using the plus (+) 'operator' in that case.
Okay, so I'm going to go back and put that back
as to what it was before.
So there's our first 'value' as number '3', so that's
two operators.
And just to confirm that, we can just do a
printout of that, and put "1 + 2 =" + result.
And probably not going to be any surprise,
any surprises to see what that comes back as,
the answer of course should be '3'.
As you can see there on the right hand side that it is.
So continuing on, another 'operator'.
What we'll do is we're going to save the result
of the previous operation.
We can use a function of 'IntelliJ' that is
to show you how to clean up if your code starts
getting disorganized or there's too many
spaces, you can come up here to [Menu bar] Code
and click on 'Reformat Code...'
and that will reformat it all for you nicely.
All right, so I'm going to create another variable called
'previousResult'.
I'm going to consign that to 'result'. So it's going to store
the current 'value' of 'result',
and then we're going to assign
the 'result' to something else. So I'm going to put
'result = result take [minus]  (-) 1.
And you've seen something similar to that
when we've taken off a value as we did in the past
So again that's using two 'operators'.
It's using equals (=) again, but it's also using
the minus sign (-), so it's subtracting.
So 'result' = whatever the count value of 'result'
which at this point in time in the code would be '3'
because that was defined up here
taking (minus) 1 from it is '2'. So we're saying 'result'
equals (=) '2' effectively.
And we can confirm that, we can put,
this time we'll put:
"result = " + result;'
so 'Run'ning that again to confirm.
Actually what we'll do just to make it a little bit more
clearer, let's put, we'll put:
previousResult [and then we're going to put]
" - 1 = " + result;
So we're just trying to...I need to put a plus (+) there as well.
So we're saying now, we're going to print out the
previousResult, take 1 = result. So it's just really
displaying on screen what we're doing in code.
So in our first one, it's 1 + 2 = 3
The next line is taking the 'previousResult' which is '3'
take 1 = 2
So that's another 'operator' the 'minus (-)'.
And if we do another one, we'll put
Well we'll need to assign 'previousResult' again, so,
'previousResult = result'.
And another one, let's do :
'result = result times [multiply] (*) by 10'
That'd be the multiplication sign (*) there,
and we can do:
'previousResult + " * 10 = " + result;'
So we'll 'Run' that.
And that's the multiplication. So we've now got
2 * 10 = 20
So that's multiplication.
Well save that value again, 'previousResult = result'.
And let's do:
'result = result [divided by (/)]  / 5;
Forward slash (/) is 'divided by'.
And again we can go and just start coping this out
here a bit. I think it'll be a bit easier then typing
it in each time.
And we'll just change this to 'divided by 5 = result'.
Let's 'Run' that.
So that's now 20 / 5 = 4.
So next, let's use another 'operator'.
This one's called the 'remainder' (%) operator.
So what we want to do with the operation is we want to
return what the 'remainder' is using two 'operands'.
And then just to be clear, the 'operands'
are these things here.
Whatever it is to the left or the right,
of an operator, that is the operand.
So in this particular case up here in the first
one we've got two 'operands', number '1'
and the number '2'. ...
They are the numbers if you like
or the parameters we are working on.
But, they are called 'operands'.
So let's do something like ...
we'll save 'previousResult' again.
And let's see if we divide the current result by 3
what are we going to be left with.
So to do that, we put:
'result = result [and we use this remainder operator] % 3'.
And what that's saying is: 'Return the result of what the
remainder is after dividing the result by '3'
So we can copy this and we'll have a look.
And we should in theory have the number '1' from that.
So if the current value is '4',
So what we're doing here is saying:
'Give me the remainder of 4 effectively less
3.' So it's taking those two off, what is the result,
what is left over after that operation.
So in this case, it should be '1'. So let's 'Run' that.
And you can see '4'. Give me the 'remainder' of 4 and 3
and the answer is '1'.
Now sometimes you might want to add a value.
I'll save the previous result again.
Something like:
'result = result + 1'
And we can just do a ... 'result'. So if we 'Run' that.
There'll be are no surprises, the 'result' is now '2'.
But there is a shortcut for that command
if you don't want to type that out, all out.
You can type 'result ++'.
So the '++' is saying 'increment the count result by one'.
And just to confirm that, we can actually print that out.
'Result is now 3', so it's adding ...
... one to whatever the count result is.
You can also use other similar 'operators'
which function probably the way you think they should.
'result --' which should deduct it.
The answer is now '2'.
So that's two examples.
The other thing we can do, we can also
abbreviate it, like so. We can put 'result += 2'.
That's saying 'result' is equivalent to putting:
'result = result + 2'
So we'll print just to confirm that.
'Result is now 4' and that's because
it was '2' in the previous print,
we've added '2' to it so the answer's '4'.
We can also do that as you would expect here:
'result *= 10'
So the count is already '4', multiplying '10' by
'4' should give us the answer '40'.
The answer is now '40'.
We can also use 'result -= 10'
Which is the abbreviation 'result = result - 10'.
And of course the answer should be '30' for that.
So the answer is '30'.
And no surprises for guessing, we can also put:
'result /= 10'
So that will be '30 / 10'.
So we should have the answer '3' if we do that.
And you can see we got the answer '3'.
So that's a lot of the common
'operators' you'll be using in your code
to perform simple mathematical functions.
What we're going to do now is start looking at
a way of expanding this and using other
types of 'operators'.
So to do that, we need to talk firstly about the
'if / then' statement.
And we'll be going into more detail
about the 'if / then' statement in future videos.
But this is a way to perform some conditional
code, depending on whether a value is 'true' or 'false'.
So the way to do that is we could start up by putting
'boolean isAlien = false'
Could be a boolean variable called 'isAlien',
and we're setting that to 'false' initially.
And we can use an 'if' statement to put:
'if [you need to use a bracket [parentheses] (isAlien == false)
then print something out, 'It is not an alien!'.
So notice something there, look at those two lines there.
Look at the 'operators'.
And you can see that one is a single equals (=),
and on the second line it's two equals (==) put together.
So the first one, the equals (=),
that is an 'assignment operator'. So we're actually saying
the value of 'false' to the 'isAlien' variable.
But the second line that's got two equals (==),
it does something completely different.
It's testing to see whether the particular value
is 'false' So in this line here,
what we're saying is:
'If the contents of the variable 'isAlien'
is false.' The two equals (==) means "it is false".
So in other words, that evaluates to 'true'.
So that statement within the brackets  [parentheses] is true.
So what we're saying is: 'Is the isAlien variable
equal to false?'
So that will evaluate to 'true' in this case
because we've set the 'false' variable to 'false'.
If it is, we're going to print out a message saying:
"It is not an alien!".
So now if we run that, we should see that will
come back and say 'It is not an alien!' on the screen.
And you can see it's come up and said 'It is not an alien!'.
However, if we change our 'if' statement,
and we change that to 'true'.
So now we're checking to see whether
the boolean 'isAlien' is set to 'true'.
So let's see what happens when we 'Run' that.
And suddenly, we've got no output.
So what's happened is the computer has
processed this line, and that has been evaluated
'isAlien' is not set to 'true'
because on the previous line we've set it to 'false'.
Because that value in the brackets [parentheses]
has evaluated has been returned as 'false',
the next line of code isn't executed.
That's conditional code. So we're only
executing that code on the next line
if the previous line was 'true', was evaluated as 'true'.
So we're using all sorts of code that sort of code
quite a bit in future videos.
So that's the effect.
And in a future video I'm going to go into more detail
and show you how you can do multiple
tests using an 'if', and you can put something called
'else' statement, so that we can evaluate
if that condition failed. So in other words, it
returned 'false'. But we won't be doing that right now.
What I'm doing now is trying to reinforce
the two equals (==) as opposed to the one equal (=).
Okay we've got some other operators to check here.
So let's create another variable.
We're going to call that: 'int topScore'
We're going to say equals 100.
So we can put a test here and put:
'if (topScore == 100);' so the two equals (==).
Then we can print out: 'You got the high score!'.
So if we 'Run' that, the moment has been evaluated
or should be evaluated to 'true'
because 'topScore' is equal to 100.
So if we 'Run' that we should see the message:
'You got the hi score!'.
But we can also do something like this, we can use
the 'not equal to' operator (!=),
that's the exclamation mark and the equal.
and that will only be displayed if 'topScore' is
'not equal to' 100.
So we can 'Run' that.
And we haven't got a result there, and the reason is
'topScore' = 100.
so that particular conditional check
there, that boolean expression if you will
evaluated to 'false'. So the next line wasn't executed.
So we can also use a 'greater than' (>) operator.
So we're testing 'is the 'topScore' greater than 100'?
So if we 'Run' that, we should finally get
no output. And the reason is the 'topScore'
is equal to 100. So the expression
'is topScore greater than 100; is 'false',
because it equals 100.
But what we can do is be all inclusive with yet
another operator, and put greater than equal (>=) to 100.
So what we're saying there is:
if the 'topScore' is greater than 100,
or it's equal to 100 print out the message.
So in that case we should see the message,
because of course 'topScore' is 100.
And now we've got the message, 'You got the topScore'.
And likewise we can put the less than sign (<).
That's another 'operator' to check to see whether
'topScore' is less than 100.
We shouldn't see the message.
But we can put less than equal (<=),
and we see the message because
'topScore' is set to 100.
And just to confirm that they both work
we can put:
'if (topScore < 100), but let's make the 'topScore' 80.
So we're doing a test now to see whether
topScore is less than 100.
So we should see that message now
because this will evaluate to 'true'.
because of course 'topScore' is less than 100.
So we 'Run' that. 'You got the high score!'
So moving on.
Let's try another one.
We'll put 'int secondTopScore = 60'.
What we can do we can put something like this.
We can put:
if (topScore > secondTopScore && topScore < 100),
print a message:
'Greater than top score and less than 100'.
So looking at that code, this is actually performing
two tests here. It's saying:
'If the topScore is greater than the secondTopScore,
[and we're also saying]
but also we want to check whether the topScore is
less than 100.'
So in this case we should find the message will be printed.
Because topScore firstly is greater than secondTopScore.
'secondTopScore' is 60 but we've assigned
80 to topScore, but we're also putting a
test 'And' (&&) if the topScore is less than 100.
and topScore is set to 80. So if we 'Run' that.
We got: ''Greater than topScore
and less than 100', We actually should have said,
'Greater than second top score', so we'll 'Run' that again.
'Greater than second top score and less than 100'
So that both of those conditions have
to be 'true' for that code to work.
And just to confirm that if we made the
the [second]TopScore 81.
We should find now that this won't show the message,
because now the topScore is not greater than
the secondTopScore.
And you can see that it hasn't been evaluated.
So that's using the ampersand (&).
So this video is getting a bit long so I'm going to stop
the video here but we'll continue on with
operators in the next video.