In the previous video we started a
discussion about operators in Java in
this video we want to got through finish
the discussion by introducing you to
some additional operators in case you're
wondering why the color on the screen
has changed since the last video
the reason is that I am re-recording this
video and that's because there were a
couple of issues with the original
recordings so its an updated version
of IntelliJ and it's now done in
this color because I'm doing that in the
later parts of this course because
it is proven to be better for the eyes in
this particular color ok so moving on so
if you recall we actually finished off
talking about the AND operator and you can see
an example of the an operator on line 55
checking to see whether both
conditions were true so both what was on
the left hand side of the 2 ampersands and also what's on the right
hand side and we would only get the output
showing on line 56
if both conditions were actually true now
what I suggest you do is in the case
where you've got these
two conditions it's a good idea to
actually put a bracket around each set
of conditions...
and you don't have to do that there are
some issues with operator precedence but
we'll talk about that later but it does
make your code easier and more
unambiguous because what you doing it's pretty clear
their that the test is now for this part here
that's the first condition in brackets
and here's the second condition in
brackets and if you run it will
still get the same output that we got
previously we got the high score but
it's just a lot clearer what's actually
going on using brackets so I do
suggest where possible with conditions
it's a good idea to put brackets around
it just to clarify ok moving on to the
next operator and what we're going to do
is talk about the OR operator now the AND
operator again both conditions with the AND
operator have to be true but with the
OR operator only one of the conditions
need to be true so lets type some code
to clarify that so put...
...I'm using the
OR which is the 2 pipe characters and the common error is using 1, 1
is actually valid but it's not all
you'll get a completely different result
and that's a same with the AND and you can have ampersand but that will give you a
different result so make sure you are
using 2 because that's the actually the
the correct and operator and
this is the correct or operator so moving on now
to test firstly to see whether top
score is greater than 90 or lets also
do a test for....and by the way I'm not sure if I showed you that
before but if you type sout as I have their
then press tab notice how IntelliJ changes that for
you and save a bit of typing...you can see what we have done their we've
said if top scorers greater than 90 or if the second top
score is less than equal to 90 then output it so if we run
this we should find that it does output because in
this example firstly on line 50 top
score is 80 so that is false
but if we look at the assignment on line
54 second top scorer is less than equal to
90 because we've assigned 81 to
that so that's true because the second
condition is true then we should get the\output showing on the screen and you
can see that we've just got one of these
tests is true
if I changed this let us make the second top
score 75 so we've now got the scenario
where on line 50 top score is 80 this
first condition is false and on line 54
second top score is 95 so the second
condition is false so therefore false or
false and we have to have at least one
true so this now should not show that
message so if we run this again one of
these test is true should not be printed
and you can see that's the case so
that's what the or operator does so I'm going to
undo that and set that back to the
original value ok so moving on
couple of little challenges here for you
just to try and figure out so let's just
start off with typing....
...now you have notice that IntelliJ is
underlining that and saying confusingly incompatible
types required boolean found int but looking
at that you think well aren't we testing to see
whether the new value is equal to 50 that 50 that is being typed their
that's the correct variable name
well what we've done there is we only used the 1 equal sign
remembering that the one
equals sign is an assignment so that is
setting the value of what's on the left
hand side to the value of 50 which is on
the right hand side so in this case that
setting the value 50 to new value or new value I should say to the value of 50 so if we wanted to
test the value if it is equal to we
need to put the two equal signs and by
doing that you can see that the error
then disappears and we can change this
because it's no longer an error
...so if we run that this is true is showing
where we had just the one equal sign of course we
couldn't run it because we actually have
an error so if we tried to run that we will actually
get an error
int could not be converted to boolean and that's because
we are trying to assign rather than set the value
so that is the equals but that's fine so that
helped IntelliJ help us their and it gave us
the error we were able to fix it
because we weren't able to get the code
running until that fix was made but there's
another scenario that can trip you up
and that's losing booleans so if we type...
....because again at face value
you will think ok if the sign false to our billion is
car on line 65 and looking quickly and on
66 we are checking to see whether isCar equals
true so surely that should fail
because isCar is false
if run this we get this is not supposed to
happen and you might be wondering what
two things here firstly why is that
happening but secondly we didn't get an
error like we did when we did the assignment
on line 62
the reason for that is when you actually
make an assignment of value any value what is
returned is whatever they assignment was so in other words in the case here
of new value equals 50 if we set it back to 1 equal sign as an expression that returns
whatever new value was assign too so in
other words that would be returned as 50
if we're actually checking the condition
now in this particular case we got an
error because when we're doing and if
comparison of course we need a boolean
to be able to determine if its true or
false so that's why IntelliJ was able to
tell us there's an error but in the second
scenario we're dealing with a boolean
already and we're assigning the value of
true to this boolean by only using the
one equal sign and consequently the
line of code actually works so that can be one to trip
you up with booleans so make sure you do
2 equal signs to avoid that error so now if we put...with
the correct two equal signs we run that we won't get
that message showing any more messages
no longer showing and the reason for
that of course is because we've correctly
done an equals test instead of trying to
do a comparison test and obviously in
that scenario another way to avoid that
with a boolean would be to just change this
and put...because by default that is not even putting
the equal signs and you're not gonna get
into difficulty and it saves you a bit of code
isCar will return whatever the value of is in this case it
will return false because we assigned it on
line 65 so run that again we shouldn't get an
error and we shouldn't get that output
and we haven't got that so that's good
last operator to discuss is the
ternary operator now this is a way to
set a value based on two conditions
so sounds confusing but let's actually
type it out and then we'll explain or talk
through it so will type....
..so this is the format
of a ternary operator so basically its saying if
is car is evaluated to true that's the
expression before the question mark so
we saying is car this the value that its
looking for
question mark is it true if so we are going to
return true and the colon is these sort
of like an otherwise return false so
again what we're saying here basically
this code is a shortcut for saying if is
car is equal equal true then was car
equal true else isCar equal false
so we are assigning that value based on whether is
car is true or false sounds a bit
confusing but lets run it to confirm and will put some code here so put
....
..so run that first we should find that it doesn't work
because of course we have assigned on line 65
isCar to false so we run that we haven't got
was car is true their so that's correct but if we change
this now and will put here..
...so we have assigned it to try so now what we're
saying is boolean is equal to the checking
that value if isCar is true it's gonna
return true otherwise it's gonna return
false so now wasCar should be equal to true because of that and if we run that we
should get the message wasCar is true
so run that wasCar is true
so their you go that is the ternary operator and again that is just a bit of a shortcut but you will see that in
Java code so it's a good thing to
actually have the knowledge under your belt
ok next i want to just go and show you
a list of operators from the Oracle
website so I'm gonna open a browser and paste this in
the link is in the Resources section you
see the link up here just let me check this
nuts and bolts not sure what happened there but
this is a handy list because it offers a
summary of all the operators and again this
link will be available in the Resources
section so some of the operators have
been discussed you can see a lot of
those have been discussed and some of
them haven't been though some of them for example the
instanceof operator will be talking
about that later in the course that's
more advance thing when we're
dealing with classes and we are not yet at that stage of the course yet but the ones down here
also the bit wise and bit shift operators
we will tackle those when if needed but
it's fairly rare that you would be
using those and if you remember early in
the video I mentioned you need to be
careful about using a single ampersand
and single pipe characte when you are
thinking about using the And
you can see that it uses a bit wise AND
with a single ampersand and a bit wise
inclusive OR for a single pipe character
that's why we need to make sure that you
typed them these ones here correctly so
you getting the right results so okay
it's time now for a challenge so lets create that back in IntelliJ and
see what you come up with
ok so here is to challenge firstly
create a double variable with a value
of 20 create a second variable of type double with a value of 80 and you want to add both
numbers up and multiply the result by 25
and you need to then used the reminder
operator which we talked about in the
previous video to figure out what the
remainder is from the sum that was
calculated in Step 3 divide by 40 and of course
that's what the remainder those and number
5 write an if statement
that displays a message saying total was
over the limit if the
remaining total which was basically using the
result of using the reminder operator
in step 4 is equal to 20 or less so go
away and do that pause the video now and when
you finish you want to come back and
compare your results to mine start the
video then so pause the video now
ok so how did you get on hopefully you figured
it out so lets now go through my version
of the code I'm gonna start on step 1
create a double variable with a value of
20 so type...
...now optionally I can put d their don't have to
put d their because in the expression
Java can figure out that we meant a
double so that's optional if you put that and will put..
....
now next we need to add both numbers up that's
the two numbers for steps one and two
and multiplied by twenty five so let's
try and type...
.....
ok step 4  use the remainder operator to
figure out the remainder from the sum of
3 divided by 40 so basically that's your not
having to re divide it again by forty
what we're trying to do is use that
remind so to do that we're going to put...
....it could be an int by the way
but we purposely doing it as a double
because we're talking about doubles here
but an int would be fine...
....this is fifth step in the if statement that
displays a message total was over the
limit if the remaining total is less
than or equal to 20 or less so we are gonna
put....
....
so that's the first cut of our code lets try actually try running that total was over the limit so what we need
to do is just try and go through this step-by-step
so what we'll do is will actually do some outputting here so
on this first line here we are gonna put...so we are just gonna display that
to the screen so you think they're in
theory
my first value plus my second value so that's a hundred times 25 should be 2500 so if you run that you can
see here we've got a weird result
we've got my total is 2020 and now
that's actually a problem even though ultimately the
last step has worked we are getting a weird
value here so why we are getting that value well this is
got to do with operator precedence so
what's happening is the order that Java
is going through to calculate these codes
are different so what we really wanted
to do was add the two values up first
my thirst value and my second and then
multiply the result by 25 but in actual
fact what's happening is because we've
used the multiplication that's got a higher
priority more higher precedence and that is being
evaluated first so what's actually happening
is we're getting 80 * 25 first
so if we have a look at that so 80 * 25 is 2000 + 20
being added to it so that's where we are getting the
2020 so what we actually need to do here
to clarify this is why brackets are
a good idea we need to tell Java calculate that first and then
multiply the result by 25 so that should give
us 2500 so let us go ahead and do that
we've now correctly got the 2500 now the
remainder basically what's left over
we've dividing 2500 effectively by 40 so that
should give us a remainder so if we have a look at our calculator how many
times does 2040 go into 2500 so its 2500 divided
by 40 that gives us 62 so 62 times
so we can do 62 times 40 that gives us 2480 so therefore if the
remainder is less than equal to 20 which
it isn't and in this case total is over the limit and just to
be sure we can actually do some output
we can print..
so run that just to clarify
that we are getting the correct results remained
is 20 rather my total is
2500 and total was over the limit
because we've successfully test to see
whether it's less than equal to 20 and
in terms of operator precedence you can
see that it's now important that you
understand operator precedence and why
you need to make sure that you get that
correct and brackets do help a lot with
that and we'll be talking more about
this in the course but for now I wanna
leave you with a website that is very
useful so if you got to another tab and paste this link and this link will be in the Resources section
so you can go ahead and check yourself this is the precedence table and
you can see more information about how
things work and can be really useful to
try and figure out when you figuring out
how these things work how Java was looking at what you're typing in to
make sure you're actually on the same
page again
some information there that is quite useful to
understand moving forward with your Java
code again the problem was issue here in
terms of precedence you can see that
operator in brackets is got the highest precedence
in Java so it looks at what's in brackets
first but going down the list you can
see here for precedence 12 multiplication divide
and modulus they've got a higher
precedence than + and that's why in our sample
code I've showed you and likewise for subtraction for that matter
that is why the code didn't work either way expected to
because it was doing the multiplication
side of things first alright so I'm going to end the video here now I hope you enjoy
that and in the
next video we're going to start talking
about some of the key words that form
part of Java language so I'll see you in
that video