In this video, we're going to make our very first
Java Application.
We're going to make an application call 'Hello World'.
Now in computing terms, it's been
a tradition, that the very first
program you create in a new language,
to get the computer to print out a message
that simply says 'Hello World'.
Nothing more, nothing less.
So the idea is just to show you some ...
basics of that language.
So what I'm going to do, I'm going to click
on 'Create New Project'.
This brings up a rather intimidating
looking screen, but it isn't as bad as it looks.
Now depending on the 'Edition' of 'IntelliJ' that
you're running. Whether you're running the
'Ultimate Edition' like I am,
or whether you're running the 'Community Edition',
you will see there's different options
here to the left hand side.
Now because I'm running the 'Ultimate Edition',
and this is the paid version of 'IntelliJ';
the 'Jetbrains' people, the makers of 'IntelliJ'
give you a lot more options.
But you don't need to worry about this
whether you're running the 'Ultimate Edition',
or running the 'Community Edition',
just make sure you click on 'java'
to the top left hand corner, like so.
Now you should also have a 'Project SDK'
showing there, and it should say something like '1.8'.
May be the future, may be a different number
but that's okay, it'll still work.
Now if you haven't got one.
Refer back to the 'SDK'
the Java Development Kit installation video,
and I actually went through and showed you how to
install a Java Development Kit.
And if you're sure you've done that
and this is not showing,
go back and check out the 'IntelliJ'
installation video.
Because right at the end of that video,
I go through and show you how to finish off
the setup of the 'Project SDK', and that involves
telling 'IntelliJ' where to find the new
Java Development Kit.
Again, make sure java is selected
leave everything else there unselected
there, we don't need to click on anything.
Click on 'Next'.
And you'll see this option
'Create project from template',
I'm going to leave that unchecked
because we want to create a brand new project
from scratch.
I'm going to click on 'Next'.
Next, it's asking you for the
'Project name' and also the 'Project location'.
'Project name' is self-explanatory. We're going to
call that one 'Hello World'.
Now I've typed it on the screen with spaces.
But I don't actually recommend you type 'spaces'.
For a project name, you want to type in whatever it is,
and you can use upper and lowercase freely.
But don't put any 'spaces' in there, and that's because
often, depending on your operating system,
you can run into difficulties with spaces
in path names.
So I suggest you leave that like so, so I'm
calling this one 'HelloWorld'.
I typed it 'correctly' this time.
And if you click on 'More Settings' down at the bottom,
you get some other options; and it gives you things like
the 'Content root', the 'Project format'
and the 'Module file location'.
We don't need to worry about any of that at this stage.
We can just stick to the basics which was the
'Project name', 'HelloWorld' and the 'Project location'.
I'm going to change this location
to another location though.
And because this is my first java application,
on this computer, you can see
I've got a 'Project location' and that's because of
I've been creating a java application
for another one of my courses, I don't want
to put my source code in there.
What I want to do is I want to click on this
button over here to the right,
and I want to navigate to a new folder
and I want to create a new folder that's
going to contain all the java code
that we'll be using for this course.
So to make it simple I'm just going to click on 'Desktop'
and I'm going to click on 'New Folder'
and I'm going to type in 'JavaPrograms'.
And click on 'Create'.
And that's going to be the folder that I'm going to
store all my java code in.
Going to click on 'Choose', and you can see it's
now updated and it's actually updated
to point to that path
But what it's done at the moment is, it's only
given me the name of the main folder.
In fact what I want to do is create a
subfolder that contains each project.
So that if I've got two projects
they've each both their own folder
in 'JavaPrograms'.
So what I'm going to do is click on again
to the right here, and I'm going to click on 'New Folder',
and I'm going to type in 'HelloWorld'.
And that's going to be the folder that
contains our first application.
So you can see now that
'Project name' is 'HelloWorld'
the 'location' is now 'Users/' in my case
dev/Desktop/JavaPrograms/HelloWorld
So it's got it's own folder and the 'Project name' is
going to be 'HelloWorld' that's stored in that folder.
Now you may have, if you're running on Windows
you'll see that this folder location will be a little bit
different. You'll probably have something like
'C:\Users (you know whatever your user name is)\
perhaps a link to the 'Documents' folder
You'll just need to navigate to a folder that
you'll remember where these files will be,
depending on your operating system.
But that's where mine are going to be.
So now I'm going to click on 'Finish'.
So what's happening now is
the 'IntelliJ' editor is now creating a folder
in that directory and it's containing the base files
that we'll be using for our application.
Now before we get started, I just want to point out
the 'Tip of the Day'.
This is a little box that comes up
every time you first start up 'IntelliJ'.
And you can turn these 'tips' off, because that's what
they are, their 'tips for the day'.
And I suggest you leave it on,
and actually read some of these. Because it
gives you some really clever shortcuts
and it gives you an overview of some of the
features that included with 'IntelliJ'.
Definitely worth your time to read some of these.
and you can click on 'Next [Tip]'
to go through and read what some of the
other tips are. And again it's just
a great way for finding out some of the
capabilities that the 'IntelliJ IDEA'
product has got.
to really save you a lot of time
when it comes to development.
I'm going to click on 'Close',
and I'm going to leave the 'Tips' On.
But if for some reason you didn't want
the 'Tips' to show, just click on the checkbox.
So what we're going to do now is click
on this little button down here to the left
which is called on a Mac a disclosure
triangle. But in any event, you'll click
that and it just opens up as you can see.
And I'm going to click here where it says
'src' which is the abbreviation for 'source'.
And what that is, is the location
where we'll be putting our java source code.
So I'm going to right-click that now.
You notice that when I click
that I get what is a huge
menu of options, and
believe if I'm not down the track
once you've had a bit of experience with java
a lot of these will make a lot more sense to you.
Right now I can see tht's
probably overwhelming but you
don't need to memorize anything.
The only thing you need to do is click on 'New'.
and come over here where it says 'Java Class',
and click on 'Java Class'.
This brings up a little window and
'IntelliJ' is now saying, 'What is the name of the
Class that you want to create?'.
Now don't worry if you don't know what a 'Class' is.
In later lectures, we're going to be going through in
detail explaining what 'Classes' are.
For now, it's just good for you to follow along
and do what I'm doing and when we get
to the stage of you needing to know more
about 'class', I'm going to go into that in more detail.
Let's create one and we're just going to call it 'Hello'.
Okay, and I'm going to click on 'OK'.
Now don't be to concerned about
the contents that are on the screen
we're going to go through that in detail in ...
... future videos. For now let's just get a basic
program up and working.
in 'IntelliJ' so that we can actually tick the
box that says we've created our
first java application, and we've actually run it.
I'm going to press 'Enter' on the end of the first line,
and I'm going to type
'public static void (I'm putting spaces between them)
Now as your typing do make sure you
type in exactly the same 'case' with exactly the
same spelling as you can see me typing.
It's very common for new programmers or people
using another programming language
to type things in to make typing mistakes
or to type things in a different case.
For example, instead of a lowercase 'p'
for the style of the word 'public', if I typed it
an uppercase 'P', you'll get a completely different result.
In this case, it's highlighted in 'red'
which is saying 'there's an error'.
So do make sure you check your code carefully
that you're typing it in exactly as you see
me type it. And if you ... see anything like
this in 'red', you can just put your mouse over it
and 'IntelliJ' will normally tell you what the problem is.
In this case it's saying "Cannot resolve symbol 'Public'"
and that's because the first letter was typed
in uppercase 'P'.
So I'm going to make that lowercase 'p' again.
So let's finish off our first program. So,
'public static void main'
With spaces in between.
then a regular 'bracket' [parenthesis].
The word 'String' with a capital 'S'.
And I'm going to put two ... square [ ] brackets
Notice those brackets a little bit different
to the other bracket's (parentheses) we've used.
and the word 'args'
I'm going to put a brace ({) now.
The brace ({)  is the same character as
the one you see after the word 'Hello'
Okay, now we've done that. Now we're going to type
'System' with a capital 'S' dot (.)
'out.printl' (and as I type the 'l')
you notice that 'IntelliJ' came up and said
'Oh do you mean 'println'?' which is an
abbreviation for 'print line'.
So if you want that and you're happy with that,
you just double-click that if you want
and you'll notice how 'IntelliJ' filled out the rest
of the line for us, which is great.
Now what I'm going to do is go back here
to this little brackets (parentheses) [println()].
And I'm going to type in a double quote (")
And notice how I only typed one double quote ("),
but 'IntelliJ' added ... the second one automatically.
And that's because 'IntelliJ'
is saying, quite rightly, 'Well if you type one
double quote (") you need to have a second one
to make it valid in java.'
So it quite conveniently added that for you.
So in those double quotes, I'm going to type 'Hello'
', World' and I'm going to put an
exclamation mark (!) after it.
So at this point, we're now
done with our first java application. We've
created a valid java application.
We know that it's valid, because there are no 'red'
errors on the screen.
We can't see any errors showing up, so
the next thing to do is to actually run the
application. So how do we actually get it
to do something? Because this
'System.out.println' or print line
which it's an abbreviation for is meant to
display 'Hello, World!' the message
somewhere on the computer.
Well it turns out, that running it is quite easy,
you just literally need to right click.
That brings up a menu with a lot of options
but the one you want is 'Run 'Hello.main()'.
So I'm going to click on that.
You notice something happened.
Something happened down at the bottom briefly
and now a little window's appeared.
And you can now see, we've actually got a message
which says 'Hello, World!'.
And it's got 'Process finished with exit code 0'.
Now we'll be talking more about what that means
in a future video, but the bottom line
is you've now created and successfully run
your first 'HelloWorld' application.
Challenge time! How would you go about modifying
the output to instead of putting 'Hello, World!',
to put 'Hello' and your name?
For example, 'Hello Tim!'
I'm going to pause the video.
Go ahead and make that change so that
the outcome becomes 'Hello Tim!'
instead of 'Hello, World!', or substitute
the word 'Tim' for 'your name'.
Go for it now!
And we'll come back shortly and
show you how to do it.
Welcome back!
So did you get that going okay?
Well it turns out the change is pretty easy.
All we really need to do is we nee go into here,
and we can go back and just delete it
as we would using a normal word processor.
Delete those characters out.
and type in your name like so.
And if you want to put in an exclamation mark (!).
Doing that, we'll actually display the
message 'Hello Tim!'.
But to see that message on the screen
again we need to right click,
and click on 'Run...'.
And you can see down on the bottom of the screen,
we've now got 'Hello Tim!' So that's it!
That's our first very basic java application.
In the next video, I'm going to walk you through
some of the basic functions within
'IntelliJ' just so you understand the various
parts of the screen, and how to move some of the
windows around depending on the amount
of screen real estate you've got.
And just to help you become a little bit more familiar
with 'IntelliJ'.
So, I'll see you in that next video.