In the previous video, we had our first
real experience with 'IntelliJ IDEA'.
We managed to create our very first 'Hello
World' application, and even modified the
program to print our name.
It's now time to explore 'IntelliJ IDEA' a little bit more.
Just to understand the various windows, and start
to understand how things are put together.
And just to have a look, and see where 'IntelliJ IDEA'
stores our files as we creating our programs.
First things first. If you look in the top of the screen
you can see the location
where 'IntelliJ IDEA' has
placed our programs. And if you remember,
in the previous video, we defined the location
where that was going to be.
So I'm going to go into that folder,
just have a look, and see what files are in there.
So, I'm going to open up my 'Finder'.
And you would open up, if you are on a 'Windows'
machine, you'd open up 'Windows Explorer'.
And you can see I'm in my 'Desktop'.
My path is 'Desktop'->'JavaPrograms'
you can see at the top there.
So I'm in the right folder. I'm going to
go into the 'HelloWorld' folder.
And you can see that there's a number of files
there that have now been added by 'IntelliJ IDEA'.
Firstly, there's a 'HelloWorld.iml'.
Now that is a file that's created by 'IntelliJ IDEA'
And that's used to keep track of the state
of this project. So it's not something you would
ever need to edit or open, or use in any way.
But you certainly wouldn't want to delete it either.
But the interesting one is in the 'src' folder.
'src' is an abbreviation for 'source'.
There's a file, and you can see it's called 'Hello.java'.
So, and that equates exactly as you can see,
just above the 'Finder' window there, 'Hello.java'.
So when you create a new 'class'
in 'IntelliJ', it creates a file, and it ends in '.java'.
So all java files that you're creating end in '.java'.
Now if you have a look in the 'out' folder,
expand that
you can see there's a 'Hello.class' file.
And looking at the sizes, you notice that
'Hello.class' is larger than the 'Hello.java'.
Now the 'Hello.class' is the compiled version
of the 'class'.
Whereas the 'Hello.java' contains the code,
as you can see on the screen there.
The 'Hello.class', if I go to open that, contains what
looks a little bit like mumbo-jumbo.
It certainly hasn't got the same code, that we
typed into the 'IntelliJ IDEA' in previous video.
A '.class' file is the compiled version of the
program, and that would be the one that
you would use to distribute and send your
code out to other people.
But we'll be talking a lot more about 'class' files
in the future videos. For now all you really need
to know is that you create programs in 'IntelliJ'
that are saved off in a file format that ends in '.java'.
And 'IntelliJ' will automatically when you 'run' the
program, create these '.class' files.
So just keep in mind that you probably don't want
to delete anything in these files for now.
You do all your changes to your java code
normally would be done in the editor itself
within in 'IntelliJ IDEA' and not anywhere else.
So going back to 'IntelliJ' now.
So over here to the left is the 'Project View',
the 'Project Window', and you can see that
the project is showing on the screen there.
If by chance yours isn't showing projects,
you can click on this 'dropdown box'
and select 'Project' from that.
And if you recall, that mirrors pretty well exactly
what we saw a minute ago in the 'Finder Window'.
So 'IntelliJ' in the  standard 'project
view' is really mirroring the contents
in the 'IntelliJ IDEA' product with what's on file.
And that's all handled for you automatically.
The other thing I want to point out, is that
you don't need to worry about 'saving' files.
In some programming languages,
you may need to actually manually save your files.
'IntelliJ' product is automatically saving things for you.
It's rare that you'll ever need too.
If you want to try and do that
for some reason, you click up here into 'File'
and click on 'Save All', but generally speaking
'IntelliJ' is handling the saving of this
behind the scenes, and writing those files out
and writing any changes you make
to those files as I showed you in the 'Finder Window'.
Now one of the other things you can do,
you can change the location of some of these windows.
For example, you might decide that down here, this
little 'Run' window, you may want that on
the right hand side instead of down at the bottom.
So what you could do, you could come over here
and click on this little 'cog'.
And when you click on 'Move to->'Right'
And you can see now, we've now got that
file on the right hand side, and of course that frees up
more room down here that was being taken up in the
past when that 'Run' window was at
the bottom of the screen.
You can also make windows bigger.
or smaller to your taste. Whatever you need.
And you can open and close a particular
window by clicking the 'View' menu
Going to 'Tool Windows'. In this case
the 'Project', if I select that again
that actually 'removes' the window from the screen.
And if I want that window to come back again,
click on 'View'->'Tool Windows' and 'Project'.
And you can see I've got a shortcut
to the right hand side there.
On a 'Mac' its 'Cmd+1'.
But that will be different,
depending if you're running 'Windows' or 'Linux'.
Just go to the relevant option, 'View'->'Tool Windows'
and you'll see what the shortcut is.
You'll end up getting to know these
quite well as you use 'IntelliJ',
and start expanding your knowledge of Java.
I'll now open up the 'Project' window again.
And you'll see that's now open.
Another thing you can do is you can set
the windows to 'floating' mode.
And to do that, click on the 'cog' for the relevant window
go down and click 'Floating Mode'.
Once you do that, you've got a free-standing window,
that you can move anywhere on the screen.
And it's not actually fixed or docked
in with the rest of the windows that are
part of 'IntelliJ IDEA'.
That could be good for example, if you
had multiple monitors and you might want to put
part of your, some of your windows
on the one monitor, and the rest on another.
And to go back, click back and again just click on
'Floating Mode' again, and that will actually
put it back where it was.
And if you want to, you can come over
here to 'Window' menu, and you could
save the current layout, if you had
a particular way you wanted to save the
windows to always go back to that particular state.
You can click on 'Store Current Layout as Default',
and then, if I go ahead and make some changes,
for example, if I move that back to the bottom again
and let's say I closed the 'Project' window,
I can come back here to 'Window'->
'Restore Default Layout',
and it actually goes back to whatever the
state was when you actually saved it.
So that can be quite handy just
to size up the windows
and to choose a format
that makes sense for you and works
with your particular setup.
So you now know the basics of how to
manipulate 'IntelliJ IDEA' and to create a
custom layout that suits your machine.
In the next Section, I'm going to start
talking more about Java,
and we're going to start learning the actual
commands and what they mean.
And specifically, we're going to start on
data types and variables,
and build our understanding from there.
So I'll see you in that next Section.