So in this section of the course,
we're going to download and install the right
version of the JDK and that's the job of
a developer's kit and then the program
we're going to use to write out Java
programs which is IntelliJ IDEA.
Now downloading and installing the right
version of Java has become a little more
complicated due to Oracle now releasing
new versions of Java every six months
instead of what used to happen when the
new version only came up once every two
to three years, but don't worry because
I'm going to make this as painless as
possible for you as we move forward,
so which version of Java or the JDK should
you install. Well, in general my advice is
to download the most recent version of
Java. As you can see on this page the
most current version of Java available
is Java 10 I recommend you download and
use that version of Java but note that
two other versions of Java are available
to download on this page Java 9 and Java 8.
So firstly Java 9 is not
recommended to use since Oracle I know
now are no longer providing support for
it but what about Java 8? Why is that
also an option for you to download?
Now the reason for this is that Java 8 is
the current LTS version of Java and LTS
stands for long-term support, so Oracle
who are the owners of Java are providing
updates to this version until at least
January 2019. Now on the other hand, Java 9
well it's already had its final
release in January 2018 and has now been
retired and will not be updated any
further, so Java 10 will then itself be
replaced by the next long-term support
version of Java which is Java 11 coming
out in September 2018. So as you can see
most versions of Java will be retired
within six months of their release with
the exception being the LTS or long term
support versions. The currently Java 8
has long term support and Java 11 is
proposed to have LTS when it comes out
later in the year. Now if all this sounds
confusing. blame Oracle. Seriously though,
well in doubt just download the latest
version of Java
that you see on this page when you visit.
Now the installation videos we'll go
through this in detail, so don't think
you need to install that now how do you
suggest you watch the installation
videos for your operating system
in this section of the course.
Now speaking of those installation videos
you'll actually see Java 8 referred to
in those videos but in general again my
recommendation is to install the very
latest version of Java you see on the
page when you go and visit and something
else to blame Oracle 4 here is that
there is an exception to this, if you've
got a 32-bit version of Windows or Linux.
Now, in your situation you'll have to
download and use the 32-bit version of
Java 8. Now the reason for that is the
newer Java versions do not have a 32-bit
version available for download and
apparently Oracle in their infinite
wisdom have decided not to offer that
from any version of Java from Java 9
onwards but that's the only exception in
in all other cases just go ahead and
download the very latest version of Java.
Now this video will be updated as needed
when Oracle changes anything and
hopefully that won't change anything
else now, but do note though irrespective
of what version of Java you download and
use you can follow along and get the
maximum value from this course.
Every thing's going to work fine, you
won't have a problem with your version
of Java and in addition, as new versions
of Java come out I'll actually be adding
a section dealing with the changes
specific to that version of Java and the
changes made to it
for those of you who want to know what
has changed and be able to take
advantage of some of the features
available in those new versions. So in
summary, so pick the very latest version
of Java that's available for you when
you get through to that download page
and refer to the installation videos in
this section for more details.
The only exception again is Windows and
Linux users if you've got a 32-bit
version of your operating system you'll
need to download Java 8 only but
again refer to your installation videos
for more details and finally
irrespective of the version of Java that
you download install, you still will be
able to make full use of all videos in
this course. So it's now time to move on,
your next steps now is to watch the
separate installation videos
your operating system, you know there's
wonderful windows another for Mac and
the third for Linux and you want to do
that for both the installation of the
Java development kit the JDK as well as
the IDE and in case you're wondering IDE
stands for integrated development
environment which is really just a fancy
word for the program we're going to be
using to write java code in this course
and that's IntelliJ IDEA. So once you do
that with both of those installations
follow along you'd be good to go and be
able to start writing some Java code.
So the windows installation video for the
Java development kit is coming up
immediately after this video so if
you're a Mac or Linux user you want to
skip ahead to the relevant video and get
in this section of the course to get
started for your operating system
otherwise, if you're a Windows user watch
the next video and we'll make a start.