In this video we're going to download
and install the Java development kit for
the Windows platform, so if you're on a
Mac or running on a Linux system refer
to the relevant video elsewhere in this
course because the steps are a little
bit different but if you're on Windows
start by going to your browser and going
to the website java.sun.com
once you get there that you see this
option over here for downloads you can
come over here and select Java SE that
brings you to this page here and for
most users you'll select this Java
platform JDK and currently you can see
as of the time of recording this video
is showing version 10 so if you're
seeing a later version then do install
that later version but there is one
caveat to that and that's if you're
running a 32-bit version of Windows.
Now if you are running a 32-bit version of
Windows you'll need to actually download
an older version of Java the JDK because
Oracle no longer supporting 32-bit
versions of Windows for our current
versions of Java or the JDK so to
determine if you're running a 32-bit or
a 64-bit version of Windows when it go
into your control panel I'm going to
right click the windows icon and select
settings that usually works for most
versions of Windows then you want to go
into system, the select system
already because I'm running Windows 10,
I can actually type system and then got an
option down here to click on about your
PC, so you may write if you're running an
older version of windows need to go to
system and then there's an option for
about any respective you should get
eventually to a screen that looks very
similar to this you can see it down here
under system type it says for me
64-bit operating system x64 based
processor so the important part is a bit
on the left which says 64-bit operating
system so that tells me that I'm running
a 64-bit version and therefore I can run
the later versions of the JDK but yours
is a 32-bit operating system then you'll
need to install the older version of the
JDK which I'll show you when we go back
to the browser how to get access to that.
Alright so let's close this down and
back in the browser so if yours said
64-bit version then you'd come down and
click on here download Java platform SDK
10 come down and click on accept license
agreement and select over here the
windows 64-bit version I'm going to save
that into my downloads folder so while
that's downloading if you found that
you're running a 32-bit version of
Windows then what you need to do is just
go back and not download this version 10
come back to this screen and scroll down
and you'll see that you'll have this
option is quite a little bit more for
version eight so come over to version
eight click on JDK download then you
have this option you can scroll down you
can accept license agreement and you can
come down here this time you select the
x86 version which is a 32-bit version
you'd select that version there and
download a that version check it out
working on your computer but again
that's only if you're running a 32-bit
version of Windows.
In my case you can see the download for
the 64-bit version has finished so I'm
going to click on that to open it so
basically just open the file you just
downloaded ok yes if you get the pop-up
to run the program I'm going to close a
browser down at this point
then we'll give the Java installation
process a chance to start ok so you can
see we got this wizard now so the first
steps is to go through and click on next
then like this folder you'll need to
possibly know this folders on my case
that's downloading to Program Files Java
JDK version 10 so I'm gonna click on
next then we'll let it go through and
install that version of Java and you do
a similar thing if you downloaded the
older version of the JDK the
installation steps are very much similar
to what you're seeing here you'd follow
those steps and you can see that it's
downloading and installing also the JRE
JRE stands for the Java Runtime edition
so installing Java and it's also
installing the JDK you need both on your
computer, click on next there again
these steps will be very similar
irrespective of whether you're running
the 32-bit or 64-bit version of the JDK,
in other words JDK 8 or JDK 10.
Alright so you'll see at this point
now the installation is now complete we
can click on close and that's the end of
the video in the next one we're going to
download install and configure the IDE
or integrated development environment
that we're going to be using to write
Java programs in this course,see you in
the next video.