In this video we're going to download
and install and configure IntelliJ IDEA
which is the integrated development
environment or IDE then we're going to
be using to write our java programs.
In this video is for the Windows platform
there's also a version for a Mac or for
a Linux machine so I refer to those
videos as appropriate, if you're on
Windows start by going to JetBrains.com
in a browser
and once that take it still that pages
kept down here we click on tools I move
over here look look okay do that and we
want this IntelliJ IDEA I will click on
download on the IntelliJ IDEA image
there and then I'll bring up this page
and when you go to download IntelliJ
IDEA you've got two options here you can
choose the ultimate or the Community
Edition. Now firstly you can see the
difference is showing here I won't go
into those now because most of those
won't make any difference to you at this
point if you're just starting out with
Java, so the Community Edition over here
on the right-hand side well that's the
free open-source version so you will
never need to pay and that's the version
that time going to install down download
and install now I'm just going to click
on that and start the download then
we'll just talk briefly about the
Ultimate Edition I'm just going to click
back to go to that previous page.
Now the other thing you can do is you can
download the Ultimate Edition and that's
got extra tools and capabilities you get
a free trial however you will need to
pay for that after the trial finishes so
for most people you probably want to
download and use the Community Edition
but what JetBrains have done is that
given me the ability to extend your
trial, so if you want to try out this
Ultimate Edition normally you give a
30-day trial I can give you an extra 90
days bringing the total trial period to
120 days so if you want to do that
download the Ultimate Edition then look
for the information in this section of
the course where I could show you how to
go about getting a key to extend that to
120 days but that's optional and as I
said the Community Edition will work
just fine in this course. Alright so I'm
just going to fast forward now and let
the rest of the IntelliJ download
complete and then we'll go through the
installation and configuration.
Okay so you can see the download is now
complete, so if I start now the process
the program rather that I've downloaded
that's going to go ahead now and install
IntelliJ Community Edition onto my
computer I'm gonna close in the browser
now we'll just go through now this
wizard to set it up I'm gonna click on
next click on next to use the default
destination folder now this part this
screen that's popped up is very
important firstly if you're running a
32-bit version of Windows and if you
don't know whether you're running a
32-bit version refer to the JDK
installation video in this section of
the course because I show you how to get
access to that but if you are running a
32-bit version and most people probably
won't be doing that but if you are if
you can 32-bit launcher and then click
on download and install JRE x86 by JetBrains,
very important that you do that because
you'll find that IntelliJ won't work
unless you do that but that's if you're
running a 32-bit version most people
will be running a 64-bit version of
Windows so that's the case select 64-bit
launcher and that's all you'll need to
do if you are running a 64-bit version
in both cases whether you're running 32 or 64-bit
I suggest you click on these three
options here Java groovy Kotlin
kt that just gives you the ability to
open files of that type in IntelliJ so
click on next now you can't install so
obviously that's now going through the
process of installing IntelliJ on this
computer. Now once that installation is
finished there's a few other things we
need to do firstly we need to configure
the Java development kit so that it it
actually works with in IntelliJ so we
need to associate the jdk
downloaded previously, so that happens
then we need to configure and tweak a
few settings within IntelliJ just to
make things a little bit easy for you to
use the Java development and once we've
done that we can then move on and start
working in IntelliJ and creating Java
programs, so I'm going to pause the video
here now and we'll come back where this
installation process has completed.
Okay, so installation is now completed we
don't want to run IntelliJ IDEA
Community Edition so I'm gonna check
their box and click on finish once
you've started IntelliJ you get this
option you can either click on the
option custom location to install it to
import rather some settings from a
previous installation of IntelliJ IDEA
or you can click on do not import
settings, in most cases do not import
settings would be the right option and
you can see that's the default I'm just
going to click on ok because I don't
want to import any settings from a
previous installation
I think this option about data sharing
I'm going to click on don't send because
I don't want to send any data to JetBrains
but you can click on send usage
statistics if you like now depending
where you are if you're in the UK or one
of the European countries that are
affected or the recent changes to data
privacy you may also get a privacy
pop-up which you'll need to agree to
before continuing but because I'm in
Australia I'm not affected by that and I
didn't get that option next you'll get
access to this screen this is a series
of customizations now for IntelliJ now
keep in mind with all of these things
that you can configure these at a later
times you don't need to spend a lot of
time thinking about this and usually
you'll see on the screen there's an
option that tells you how to get access
to these things to change in the future
this one is the background I'm going to
click on IntelliJ this is white
background which tends to be better for
video you can choose either click on
next now this screen gives you a list of
default plugins for IntelliJ one thing
you'll find with IntelliJ it's very
versatile and there's lots of different
plugins that you can install to add
various functionality
what I suggest here is you just leave
everything as the default noting that
you can change this again in the future
and one other note to keep in mind here
is if you're installing the ultimate
edition of IntelliJ you'll find that
there's more options on this screen in
both cases I just recommend you click on next
same deal on this screen you can install
these things if you want to but I
suggest you leave them and you can
always come back later to do that I'm
going to click on start now using
IntelliJ IDEA so we've now loaded
IntelliJ for the first time next thing
we want to do now is we want to
associate the Java development kit that
we installed in the previous video so
come down here click on configure click
on project defaults and click on project
structure this gives us the screen here
and we need to now define or select the
software development kit that we want to
use, so you may need to click on SDKs
here but usually from project will be
have to do the same thing so we'll just
click on this little drop down we can
confirm that there's no SDK or software
development kit installed so I'm going
to click on new I'm going to select JDK
because we want to install a new Java
development kit all he set it up then we
need to navigate to the folder where the
JDK was installed you remember that
remember that I discussed that in the
last video and showed you where that was
in most cases that will be in the C
Drive Program Files noting that I'm not
selecting Program Files x86 that's a
different folder altogether Java and JDK
so I'm going to select a JDK now
depending on the version you've
downloaded the numbers will change you
can see here that I've got an older
version here Java 8 1.8 means Java
version 8 that would be situation yet
that's that would be the one you choose
if you have a 32-bit version of Windows
but in my case I had a 64-bit version of
Windows running and I'm gonna just click
on this first option here for JDK making
sure that it's the latest version that
is available in this in this folder
one other thing make sure you don't
click the JRE, JRE stands for Runtime
Edition, Java Runtime Edition JDK is Java
development kit, you need to click on the
Java development kit click on OK and you
can see now that we've got a
configuration here whereas before it
said no JDK we've got Java 10 showing
the other thing is just to make sure you
select the right version here the
project level
it's normally auto selected for you in
my case you can see it's set to 10 and
that means that we're going to be using
the features of Java 10 if you had to
install a JDK 8 you would select a
version 8, in my case version 10 is
correct so I'm gonna click on ok so
we've now configured to the Java
development kit there's just a few other
settings to configure that I recommend
you set and you get access to those I'm
going to click on configure and select
settings once that pops up we want to
come down to editor click on the little
triangle there to expand it then come
down to general and click that as well
and then click on auto import 2 very
useful checkboxes to check here would be
the add and an unambiguous imports on
the fly and optimize imports on the fly
at the current project or select you,
I suggest you configure both of those or
select both
those come down to appearance I suggest
you click on I might will make sure that
the show line numbers checkbox is
checked in this case you can see that it
is checked and I don't need to do
anything there and finally come down
here to code folding and what I
recommend you do here is I recommend you
take off the check boxes for closures
and for generic constructor and method
parameters and the reason will become
apparent is to go through the course it
just makes sure that tell the code that
we're writing isn't being hidden away by
IntelliJ, alright once I click on ok and that
will save those changes in your
configuration and it means that all
future projects that you create when the
IntelliJ will use those settings. Alright,
so this point we're done we've now
configured IntelliJ IDEA and you're
ready to move on now to the next video.