In this video we're going to download
and install the Java development kit for
a Mac computer and if you're running on
Windows or a Linux machine refer to the
separate videos in this course for those
operating systems but if you're on a Mac
go to Java sun.com in a browser once you
get there select Java SE we come over
here and select or click Java platform
SDK, and click on accept license
agreement come over to the back version
click on that and select save to start
the download. Now the version that I will
show on this page may change as of the
time that I'm recording this video you
can see that it's got Java SE
development kit 10.0.1 so that is
the most current release but if you've
got a later version or you see a later
version on this page just select that
and download that version because things
will still work just fine in this course.
Alright so I'm going to pause now until
this download is complete and then we'll
go through the installation process.
Alright so the download is now complete so
I'm going to come down here and click on
the dmg file to open it
and then we're going to start with the
installation I'm gonna double click on
this icon to start it we click on
continue I'm going to click on install
type in my password and then start the
installation after I press enter.
I can click on close, now this option that
will either delete the file that you
download it or put it into the trash or
you can optionally select to I keep it
this can be useful to keep it if you
plan to install this on another computer
just to save you having to download it
in my case, I'm just going to click
on move to trash and installations now
completed I can close down that window
as well. So in the next video
now that we've installed Java
development kit we need to download
install and configure the actual program
we're going to be using to create Java
applications in this course and that's
called IntelliJ IDEA. So let's work on
that in the next video.