In this video we're going to download and
install IntelliJ which is the IDE or
integrated development environment that
we're going to be using in this course
to create our Java programs. Now this
video is for a Mac so if you're on a
Windows machine or a Linux machine refer
to the appropriate video for your
operating system as there are a few
differences when it comes to downloading
and installing. Okay so in the browser
firstly you wanna go to JetBrains.com
and JetBrains is the name of the company
who have created this product we're
going to be using IntelliJ IDEA once we
get to that page when I click on tools
they want to come over here to IntelliJ
IDEA and click that and that brings us
to a page with information relating to
IntelliJ. Now there's two versions of
IntelliJ that we can install and if we
scroll it towards the bottom of the page
you can see that there's a comparison
chart between the two versions so we've
got the Ultimate Edition for web and
Enterprise Development and the Community
Edition for JVM which are a virtual
machine and Android development now the
differences are the Ultimate Edition is
a paid version of IntelliJ if we scroll
down a little bit you can see there's a
free trial available but after that the
trial period has expired
you will need to pay for the product
that's the Ultimate Edition, the
Community Edition on the other hand has
less features but is completely free and
open source and you'll never need to pay
for it. In this course the community
version will suffice there's really no
reason to buy the Ultimate Edition but
if you want to do that for some reason
you can take the trial the other thing I
can do is that I can extend the trial by
90 days to give you a total of 120 days
trial of the Ultimate Edition but in my
case what I'm going to do is download
the free community edition I'm gonna
click on download give that a moment to
start and I'm just going to save it to
my computer and I'll pause the video now
we'll come back once it's fully
downloaded and we'll continue on with
the installation and configuration.
Okay, so the download is now complete so I'm
going to come over here and click on the
dmg file which will start the
installation process on my back and I'm
gonna take the opportunity to close down
the browser since we're finished with
the download,
once it starts we've got the option to
install and all we need to do is click
on the IntelliJ seee icon holding the
button down and drag it to the
Applications folder and release
and the installation is now completed so
I'm going to close this down and what
I'm going to do is start IntelliJ so I'm
going to do is now open a window go to
my Applications folder and I'm going to
choose IntelliJ seee which is the
Community Edition that I've downloaded
double click that to start the
installation process,
okay when this option comes up we're
going to click on open and the first
time you've installed IntelliJ IDEA
you've got the option here to import the
settings from another custom location or
to not import any settings in this case
I haven't got anywhere else to load the
settings from so I'm going to leave the
default option selected dunno the import
settings and click ok. Now between when
I've clicked ok and this screen popping
up if you're in the Europe and you're
affected by the recent Tubb privacy
updates that are carrying in May 2018
you may see a pop-up asking you to
accept privacy terms and conditions so
that does pop up for you accept those in
my case because up on Australia I'm not
affected so I don't need to select
anything and then you'll move on and
you'll get to the screen this screen
gives you the option of a siding a theme
for IntelliJ and essentially what it is
is just the color style or theme that's
going to be used during development.
Now keep in mind I'm gonna select light here
keep in mind that you can change these
appearances later and it gives you the
options here on how to find out how to
do that by going to appearances
appearance of behavior and appearance so
that's where you'll change it if you
like but I'm going to select that
default and click on next on this screen
you select the key map scheme in almost
all cases you'll select the option on
the left hand side I've never used ID
and just let the default key map for
IntelliJ IDEA so next this screen gives
you the ability to run the IntelliJ IDEA
from the command line I'm not going to
be doing that in this course because I
prefer to start the GUI interface and
load my code and projects etc from there
but if for some reason you want to be
over the ability to run IntelliJ from
the command line this would be where
you'd select that click on next
so IntelliJ IDEA is a very versatile
program, it's got lots of different
plugins and settings that you can
configure and this screens giving you
the ability to choose some and basically
the list of tools that are enabled by
default. Now what I suggest you do here
is just leave everything else is and
move on to the next screen noting that
you can always install additional
plugins and uninstall them etc later on
the other thing I want to point out here
is if you're running the intelligent
edition of IntelliJ IDEA you'll see that
that'll have even more options than what
the ones than the ones that I was
actually showing here that's because
because you're paying for the ultimate
edition they give you extra plugins and
so forth to use in this case I'm just
going to click on next
same deal here with the featured plugins
I'm going to leave everything as its
default but if you wanted to you can
make a change but again you can always
go back into preferences plugins later
and configure things at some future
point in time, so I'm going to click on
start using IntelliJ IDEA at this point
we've now got IntelliJ IDEA installed.
Now what we need to do is make some
configuration changes, firstly to I
configure the Java development kit so
that works with IntelliJ and then
there's a few other settings we need to
make so to get access to the JDK we're
gonna click on configure select project
defaults and select the project
structure that brings up this screen
here and initially when we go in here
you'll see that it says no SDK ok on the
drop down there's nothing there so what
we need to do is configure the Java
development kit to work with IntelliJ
IDEA click on new to do that, we select
JDK got lots of options here because
IntelliJ IDEA is a versatile IDE that
works with a number of different
languages but we want the JDK here so
click on that and what should happen is
that IntelliJ IDEA should find the
installation of JDK 10 that we've only
just installed in the previous video so
right click the drop down here you can
see that if I come down here and have a
look in jdk 10.01, jdk so that's the jdk
that we installed and it should update
and find the one for you automatically
if not you'd go to your library folder
as you can see there select java java
virtual machines you choose the jdk and
going to the contents home for her but
in my case it found it automatically so
i just need to click on open and you can
see what's happened there now that
that's been selected you can see we've
now got a project SDK here now showing
Java 10, the other thing you want to make
sure you've selected here is to set the
SDK at the default in my case you can
see that it did actually sell it
automatically but it should be set to 10
which may basically means you get access
to all the features for that particular
version of Java. Alright so at this point
that's now
complete so click on ok to save those
settings and we're nearly finished now
there's just a few other configuration
settings we need to set before we can
start actually creating some Java
programs so to get access to those
settings we're going to configure you
want to click on preferences next we
want to come down here and they click on
the little triangle next to editor click
on it again the one that's next to
general then click on auto import
there's two options here add an
ambiguous imports on-the-fly check that
there's also optimized imports on the
fly for current project click on check
that box as well and without going into
too much detail at the moment it just
makes things a little bit easier to work
with by automating some of the things
that say you would perhaps have to have
done manually as a Java developer in the
past we'll talk more about that when we
get to that appropriate stage in the
course, next we want to come down to
appearance and click on appearance you
want to make sure that show align
numbers is checked unless you can see in
my case it was checked by default but if
it's not checked on your installations
for whatever reason make sure you check
that and finally when it come down here
to code folding you click on that and
you want to make sure here is that
closures is deselected and uncheck that
and also generic constructor and method
parameters we're gonna uncheck that as
well, so what code following is it's
actually hiding some of the source code
that programmers don't need to access
very often but in our particular case
because we're starting out learning Java
it's best that we see all the code and
that the IDE doesn't try to
hide anything from us so that's why
we've done that and the other thing here
is you're going to also take the check
box off one-line methods once we've done
that we can click on ok and at this
point, we're now fully configured
IntelliJ IDEA and the JDK and we're
ready to start creating our first Java
program. So let's end the video here in
the next video it's time to start
writing as I mentioned the Java program
so you want to skip this the videos that
relate to setting up the JDK and
IntelliJ IDEA for different platforms
because we're now set up and configured
on the Mac and you can move on then
those videos and go to the next video
when we start talking about creating
some programs, so I'll see you in the next video.