In this video we're going to download
and install the Java development kit, JDK
for a linux platform. Now I'm running
this on Ubuntu 16.04 but it should work
without any issues on later versions,
so what we need to do is go to a command
line I'm going to open the command
window close down this browser and we're
going to do is we're gonna start by
typing sudo space a it add apt
repository space ppa:linuxuprising
slash Java type in your
password press enter next we're gonna
type sudo space apt - get space update
press Enter you met a moment to complete
you know when that's finished we're
gonna type sudo space apt - get space
install space Oracle
- Java 10 - install, so obviously I'm
installing Java 10 here and you will
occasionally get a message like that you
can try that again if you get the same
problem, I found you can actually close
down to exit and open a terminal session
again and top the command again sudo
space apt - get space install space
Oracle Java 10 - install password and
you have no luck with that again this
does happen from time to time we can try
configure gate manually but I was quite
honestly the easiest way to get around
this is just to restart your
installation, so I'm going to do that I'm
gonna click on shutdown and then restart
restart Ubuntu and once they restart we
should find that that error has
disappeared. Okay, I'm gonna login
can't get over my terminal again third
time lucky we're going to type just that
through command again sudo space apt -
get space install space then it's Oracle
- Java 10 - install type in my password
you can see that this time it's actually
worked, some I click on type y
center and what's happening now is it's
downloading, you can see they're added now
configuring the Oracle Java 10
installers I'm gonna click ok there by
pressing enter I'm gonna move the arrow
and I've used press the left arrow to
select yes and press enter
accepted the license as you can see it's
now downloading Java 10 from Oracle's
website so that's going to take live a
while it's going to take a few minutes
as you can see before that completes the
good thing about this process is it's
quite fast and there's no other steps
there's another alternative where you
can manually install the the JDK if you
prefer to use the open JDK version
instead of Oracle's version what I'll do
is I'll post some notes in the resources
section of this video if you want to do
that instead of downloading Oracle's
version of Java.
You can see the Downloads complete now,
and it's now going through the process
of installing the downloaded version of
Java 10 to this installation and at this
point we've now finished the
configuration and you can see there's
always have an additional command to
type there to setup JDK 10 as the
default so I'm going to do that I going
to type sudo space apt space install
space Oracle
- Java 10 - set - default press enter
there we've now set to have a ten to be
the default installation of Java on this
computer, we can verify that by typing
Java space - - version and you can see
it shows us and confirms that we're
running Java version 10.0
in this computer. Alright so that's the
installation of the Java development kit
a complete, in the next video what we
need to do is download and install the
IDE or integrated development
environment, so we're going to be using
on this computer to write programs and
then IDE is called IntelliJ IDEA so
let's work on that in the next video.