In this video we're going to download
install and configure the IDE IntelliJ
IDEA that we're going to be using in
this course to write Java programs.
Now this video is for a Linux platform so if
you're on another operating system do
refer to the relevant video for your
operating system but if you're running
Linux, then open a browser then want to
go to www.jetbrains.com. Now JetBrains are the
people who have created IntelliJ IDEA so
once you get to that site click on tools
come over here and click on IntelliJ IDEA,
then IntelliJ IDEA comes in two versions
if we scroll down and have a look we can
find out some more information about
what each version is all about, you can
see that we've got an Ultimate Edition
here for web and enterprise development
and a community edition, the JVM and
Android development license top is
commercial the Ultimate Edition an
open-source for the Community Edition so
effectively what that means is the
Community Edition is free and we can
confirm that down here and the ultimate
edition gives you a trial period after
the trial expires will then need to
purchase that software, by default the
Ultimate Edition gives you a 30-day
trial I can extend that by another 90
days to a total of 100 120 days if you
want to try out the Ultimate Edition but
that's your choice either one will work
I recommend that the Community Edition
is quite acceptable and everything that
we do with this course will work just
fine with that edition. So that's reason
I'm going to click on download for the
Community Edition
and I'm going to save that so I'll saved
to my download directory and we'll start
that once that's finished.
Alright first you can see the download
is now complete, so I'm going to come
over here and click on the little folder
there to open the folder and we need to
decide on a location where we're going
to install this. Now where exactly
install it is up to you what I'm going
to do is click on my home folder I'm
going to create a new folder and call it dev
and we're going to put that in IntelliJ
IDEA as a subfolder from that folder
that's where I'm going to put all my
development tools, so I don't I'm not
going to go to downloads I'm going to
double click the archive the target GZ
file to open it then I'm going to
extract that and then you go back to my
home folder into my dev folder I'm going
to extract it into that folder I need to
click on close I'm going to close down
the extractor now we're finished with
that I'm also going to take the
opportunity to close down this screen as
well we've done with that as well
and the browser what we're going to do
now is go to the command bar line our
terminal session and we're going to
start IntelliJ IDEA for the first time
via the command line let's go ahead and
do that so I'm going to first go into
the folder it's on a CD space
forward slash dev slash I'm going to
type I and press tab and then we'll go
into the quad folder for the IntelliJ
automatically then I'm going to type CD
space bin and they're going to type ls,
press enter and that's now the bin
folder which contains the versions,
I mean version of IntelliJ that we want to
run so going to type a period forward
slash idea
dot sh that's the script to startup
idea IntelliJ IDEA for the first time as
it's standing up you can see here
there's asking us whether we want to
import IntelliJ IDEA settings from
another location or what do we not want
to import settings I'm going to choose
do not import but if you do have a
location wave installed an installation
of IntelliJ IDEA previously and you want
to retain the settings you would choose
that folder and IntelliJ would
automatically install those settings but
I'm just going to click on ok with the
option do not import settings checked
next you may or may not get this update
this is the privacy policy that
appears and I'm just going to screw it
into the bottom here and click on accept
next we'll get data sharing I'm gonna
click on don't send but if you want to
share statistics for some reason you can
choose that I'm going to look on don't
send next we get to the stage where
we're doing some initial customization
our IntelliJ IDEA, you can see this
option here gives us dark color IntelliJ
IDEA and gtk+ you got three styles or
themes that you can choose the one that
I generally like is the IntelliJ one so
that's what I'm going to select keep in
mind you can also change these settings
later by going into settings appearance
and behavior and appearance, so click on
next, so next is saying do we want to
create a desktop entry to make it easier
to start this from the GUI interface
definitely I want that so I'm going to
leave the default selected there if for
some reason you don't want to do that
now go into tools and create desktop
entries how you get access to that
within IntelliJ at a later stage
click on next the launcher script can be
handy if you're often in the command
line and you want to invoke IntelliJ
from the command line or open a
particular file from the command line
I generally don't do that I generally
just starting intelliJ and then do all my
phone navigation and opening of projects
within the GUI interface if for some
reason you want the script you check
that I'm gonna leave it unchecked click
on next default plugins here we get a
list of default plugins they're going to
be configured and installed by IntelliJ
generally I suggest you leave this
because you can always go ahead and
install plugins at your leisure or
install plugins within the settings in a
later time so I'm gonna leave the
default they're just one quick thing to
keep in mind is if you installed the
Ultimate Edition you will follow there's
a lot more options that are shown on the
screen than the ones you can see here.
Alright so gonna click on next
same deal here with featured plugins I
suggest you leave it as is but you can
select install them if that's what you
want to do but I'm not going to do
anything there I was going to click
start using IntelliJ IDEA
so at that point the basic installation
of IntelliJ IDEA was now complete but
there's a few other things we need to
configure, firstly we need to be
configure IntelliJ IDEA to point it to
the Java development kit so that could
find the Java development kit so that we
can create Java programs so to do that
we're gonna click on configure I'm going
to click on project defaults we're going
to select project structure that brings
this screen up and what we didn't want
to do is come over here you should find
if we click on the drop box there's no
other SDK so in other words until today
ID hasn't configured anything so I'm
going to come over here and click on new,
now IntelliJ IDEA and that was you to
edit code in a variety of languages so
when we click on new for a project SDK,
we need to choose the type and you may may
or may not have all these options or you
may even have additional options I'm
going to select JDK since we configuring
IntelliJ IDE for Java. Now you notice
what happened then automatically
IntelliJ IDEA found our java 10
installation and that should generally
be the case for you and you shouldn't
need to configure it so I'm just going
to click on ok there we've got Java 10
configured but if for some reason it
wasn't automatically configured you just
need to navigate to the folder where
Java 10 was installed and in choose that
folder so that the installation will
proceed the other thing we want to do is
make sure that STK default is selected
first going to give us full access
to the version of the JDK we've
installed 10 in this case so I'm gonna
click on account of that and we've now
configured IntelliJ IDEA for Java
there's just a few other things that we
need to configure before we end the
video, so come up here and click on
configure they want to click on settings
next thing we want to do is come down to
edit so click on this little arrow to
the left of editor come down here and
click a little arrow to left a general
then we wanna click on auto import
you want to make sure both these options
optimize import on the fly and also add
an ambiguous imports on the fly are both
checked they want to come down to
appearance we want to make sure that
show line numbers is checked now that's
generally the default these days for
IntelliJ IDEA
but it's a good thing to check too
that is checked which it is in this case
then we want to go to code forwarding
click on that and we want to deselect a
few things here we want to deselect one
line methods and also deselect closures
and then also generic constructor and
method parameters so what we're doing
here is we were stopping IntelliJ from
folding the code or hiding some of the
source code from us the code folding
heap feature can be very useful for
experienced developers who want to hide
portions of their code but in our case
because we're just starting out learning
Java for the first time we want to see
all our code so what we're doing is
we're turning off those options so that
we get to see instead of a further code
being folded and hidden we can see
everything we're gonna see all that Java
code so once we've done that you can
click on ok you're going to close down
IntelliJ IDEA and we're going to do is
top exit so closely in the terminal
window and now that we'll just hold a
desktop entry we should be able to come
over here and click type of the first
few letters of intelliJ
this case and check that or click that
rather and you can see that we've got
the ability to install or to run rather
IntelliJ IDEA from one click of the
mouse. Alright so that's our
installation complete, let's now move
on to the next video, we're going to
start taking a look at IntelliJ
specifically we're going to start
creating a Java program, so I'll see you
in the next video.