In the previous video we went ahead and
discussed statements, white space and
indenting.
It's now time to move on
to the if keyword and
also discuss code blocks in more detail.
So, as you can see,
I've created a new project.
I've called it if keyword and code blocks.
So what I wanna do first is just go
through the if keyword a little bit
more so you're familiar with the various
ways that you can actually use it.
So what we're going to do is create
some code and then go through it.
So, I'm going to start with some code and
then delete that comment and
put boolean gameOver = true.
Int score equals 5000.
Int levelCompleted = 5.
Int bonus = 100.
So we can use the if keyword to create
a statement something along the lines of,
if score equals, double equals because
we're doing a test, equals 5,000.
We can use the brace to
create a code block or
we can put something like printin.
Your score was 5000.
Okay, so we can just run that.
So as you can see,
the if statement was pretty basic and
it printed out your score was 5000.
Just making more space here.
So, that's the first use
of the if that you've seen.
But we can actually also do this.
We can get rid of these braces, in other
words, get rid of the code block if we've
only got one line, one statement that
we want to get executed after the test.
So in this case,
if the score equals 5,000,
if that's true, it's going to run that and
execute that, like you just saw me run.
If it's not true, it's just going to
ignore that and go on to the next line.
So again we can run it,
just to confirm that it's gonna work.
We still get the same response,
we still get the score is 5000.
What we can't do without the code block,
without adding the braces,
is we can't put another line here.
Cuz what happens?
As you'll see, run that again.
This was executed as well, but
if we change this if so that it's 4000.
And of course we set the score to 5000 so
we shouldn't see your score is 5000 on
screen now because
the comparison will fail.
But the output this was
executed was still executed.
So what's happening is that this is being
executed no matter what because it's not
on the line after the if test.
And that's because only
one line without a code,
like without adding these braces, we can
literally only process one line at a time.
If I add the braces, so in other words,
if I create a code block and
put that code in there, then that
will quite happily work here on that.
And you get no output because, of course,
the score isn't 4000, it's 5000.
If we change the comparison so
that it's 5000, we get both because
it´s actually in the code block.
So, the use of code blocks
are optional if you´ve only got
one statement you want to process.
What I generally recommend is even
if you've got only the one line,
to probably use a code block anyway.
And that's because I believe it
actually makes the code clearer and
easy to understand.
So, removing the code block.
Just sometimes, at a glance, if there's
a space there which Java accepts,
sometimes you might get a little bit
confused at first glance and wonder
whether this is all part and parcel of the
same if keyword statement, if you will.
But the other thing you can do,
if I put the code block back now,
let's change this around a bit.
I wanna show you the other parts of
the if, which I know we've talked about
a little bit, but
just to make it a little more clearer.
So I can put something like if
score is less the 5000, score was.
Less than 5000, or we can also just put
an else, else, and put a code block.
So what will happen there,
we can put something like.
Got here.
Well, just to see what happens,
and if we run that.
We got here, and the reason that we
got here and we didn't see any other
output is the first if test was checked,
so is score less than 5000?
No, it wasn't.
So this line, this code block was
not executed as a result of that.
So what happens then is
the computer goes on and,
to the next part here
which is an l statement.
And because we've got no other
condition there, it says okay,
in all other circumstances I'm
going to just print got here.
And that's why it printed got here.
If we then change this to put
it less than or equal to 5000.
We get the message, your score was less
than 5000, and now the else wasn't
executed So this line didn't get executed
because the first condition was fulfilled.
So you can see that the if is
useful from that scenario, but
we can even expand it further.
What we can do is we can put
something like so we'll do that test,
it was less than 5000.
We can also do something like
else if(score < 1000).
Create another one.
And I'll change that so it's < 5000.
Then we use and > 1000.
Then we can put this here.
Your score was less than 5000 but
greater than 1000.
Then we can put else if(score less than
1000), we can put some output,
your score was less than 1000.
You'll need to put
a variable name in there.
Score.
So now what will happen is if the score is
less than 5000 but it's greater than 1000,
it's gonna put that message.
Notice if the score was less than 1000,
the score is gonna show that message,
your score was less than one thousand.
Otherwise, it's gonna go to got here.
So let's try and see what happens there.
Got here.
It was executed because,
of course, these first two lines aren't
processed because in both cases,
the comparison tests there have failed.
So, score is 5000 and
score is greater than 1000.
And what neither of us know is because
score is currently set to 5000.
We could change that to check that
it's working by making that 4000.
So if you run that, your score was
less than 5000 but greater than 1000.
So it's now executed its first component,
and you can see that it's
automatically jumping out of the section
after it's executed something.
So as soon as it's found something,
it's going to ignore the else if and
any other subsequent elses along the way.
And just to confirm that we can then
make the score to be 800 and run that.
We've now got your score
was less than 1000, so
you can see there so
that's only executed this section here.
So this can be very useful,
to use the if keyword
to build up statements to test a lot
of scenarios and to proceed and
execute certain code based on what
the results of those comparisons were.
So that's the if keyword.
I hope that's given you
a bit more clarification.
So let's now just take
it to the next level.
What I am going to do
is highlight that code.
I'm just gonna comment that out.
On a Mac I can hold down Cmd+/.
You could also have gone
up to the code menu and
selected Comment with Line Comment.
And you can see to the right
there is the command slash,
is the keyboard shortcut on a Mac.
So check that out on your operating
system to see what the shortcut is.
So what we wanna do is,
is we wanna do a test here.
We wanna put if(gameOver = true)
You wanna print out,
your final score was, final score.
So if you run that.
We can see that the final
score is 1300 and
that's because the final score equals the
score, which was 800 plus levelCompleted,
which is five,
times our bonus, which is 100.
So therefore, it's 800 plus 500 and
the finalScore was 1300.
So you can see that the code block,
as we've done before,
was executed because gameOver,
of course, was set to true.
But notice how we've created
a variable in the code block.
And the thing to remember about code
blocks is, as you can see here,
they're able to access variables that
were created outside of the code block.
So you can see that we've accessed score,
as you can see score there,
level completed and bonus.
All these variables were created
outside of the code block.
But final score was created,
the variable Inside the code block.
What we can't do is we can't
put something like this,
int savedFinalScore=finalScore.
And IntelliJ comes up with an error and
it says cannot resolve symbol finalScore.
And that's because once this
section of code has finished,
in other words the computer
has processed it,
it will automatically delete any variables
that it creates in that code block.
So, the reverse isn't true.
While you can access variables created
outside of the code block in the code
block, what you can't do is
access variables created in
the code block outside of the code block
as you can see in this scenario there.
And just as another abbreviation, you can
also, when you see something like this,
game over equals equals true,
that can be abbreviated to, if game over.
So, that essentially is exactly the same
as typing if gameOver equals equals true.
So keep that in mind as a way
to abbreviate your code.
You'll see that commonly
used in Java code.
There's just a shortcut to test to see
whether gameOver has the value true.
So this concept of variables inside
a code block is called scope.
And scope is something that requires
video as a sign of arrival.
We'll be talking more about
scope in future videos.
And scope really deals with accessibility
of variables in certain situations or
in certain places in the code for
example, in a code block.
The bottom line for now is,
in a code block if you create a variable,
you can't access that variable you've
created outside of that code block.
But of course, you can as you saw,
still access variables that
were created previously and
prior to going into the code block
whilst you're in the code block itself.
Okay, so, it's challenge time.
Okay, so the challenge for you now is to
create a second printout on the screen,
this time with the score set to 10,000
with the level completed set to eight and
with the bonus set to 200.
So you need to do something very similar
to what we've done here in this first
example, but you need to also make
sure that this still displays.
So that essentially you'll have this first
one displaying, you'll then blow that,
have a second line with
the scenario here also displaying.
And both of them should be displaying
here in the right-hand corner.
All right, so go to it.
Pause the video and go ahead and
see if you can implement that.
And when you're ready, start the video
again and come back and see my solution.
So how did you get on,
did you figure it out?
Well, there's a couple of
ways to go about this.
What we could do,
the first approach would be to create
a complete new set of variables and
to essentially do a copy and paste of that
code but use all the new variable names.
So that would work.
We could do something like Copy,
and we'll call this,
New game over, new score,
new level completed, new bonus.
And then we could do something like.
And then we could do something like new
score equals new level
completed times new bonus.
And note how I can still use the int
final score in this second code block,
because if you remember as soon
as the code block is finished,
Java will automatically delete that.
So, that's why we're able to re-create
another variable with the same name again.
Of course, we weren't able to do that
with these variables because they're
in the same scope, effectively,
the same part of the code.
And the other thing I need to do is
change that gameOver to newGameOver.
So we could do that,
and if we run that, so
far we've got, oops,
newScore was meant to be 10,000.
Change these to the level is 8 and
200, that is what we're looking for.
So we run that again,
get the answer 11,600,
which is 10,000 plus 8 times 200 is 1600.
10,000 plus 1600 equals 11,600.
So that's certainly one solution to it,
creating all new variables.
The disadvantage with that approach
is you're using excess memory so
you're creating new variables
that you don't potentially need.
So what you could do as an alternative,
we could have just reused
those variables again.
So what we could have done is I'm
just gonna cut that code out.
I could have just copied these.
This time I'll get rid of the definitions
because we're not redefining them,
we're just changing the values.
So we can make that 10,000 Level 8 and
200.
And then we can literally just copy and
paste this section of code again.
Paste that in because it's exactly the
same, we're using the same variable names.
Everything else should be the same, so
we should get the same output here.
So we run that.
So that's another way of doing it.
That's just literally copying and pasting.
The advantage with that approach is it was
quicker, we didn't create new variables.
So we used the memory more efficiently.
But the disadvantages, firstly, we haven't
got a permanent record of these variables.
So if we wanted to keep the fact
that this first goal was 800 and
the level was completed was 5 and
bonus was 100,
we can't do that because we have
now redefined the variables.
Secondly, we've used game over equals true
for both and if you were tracking two
players' scores maybe game over
was only the case for one of them.
So in this case you may not have
actually printed this out at all because
it was set to false.
But the other disadvantage is
we're copying and pasting cod.
And the disadvantage with copying and
pasting code is we're duplicating code.
And what that means if we
need to make a change,
then what we need to do is change
it in more than one place, and
if you forget that your code is,
your code has been duplicated.
You may forget to change in one place,
which means your scores may
not be calculated correctly.
For example, let's just say we've
decided to change the formula for
defining our final score.
And we're gonna add a bonus of 1000 to
the final score that was calculated.
So we come along here and we put +.
So just on the next line
we could put final score.
Plus equals 1000.
So that's an overall final bonus.
So if we run this.
You can see the first
score was correctly set
to 2300 which was the 1300
plus the 1000 bonus.
But down here we forgot to make
the change in this particular code block.
And as a result that final score
didn't have the final 1000 points
added to it correctly.
That's the disadvantage with duplication.
You need to go back and remember all the
places where the code is duplicated and
to make your change.
So you're really asking for errors in
the long term because, let's face it,
we're all human.
We make mistakes, we forget things.
And it is very common in programming,
particularly as the code you
work on gets more complicated.
To forget, if you are duplicating
a lot of code, where all that code is.
So you definitely don't wanna get into
that scenario of duplicating your code.
And there are lots of ways
to help really reduce or
eliminate the need pretty much for
any duplicate code.
So, in the next video, I'm going
to expand on from this example and
show you how you can remove duplication
by using the concept of methods.
So, methods is taking the concept of
a code block to the next level, and
it's going to effectively
allow you to reuse that code.
So type the code once and
reuse it multiple times.
So we'll do that in the next video.