Now just before we move on to the next
video, which is about method overloading
there is still another small logical
problem in our conditions in the program
that we've been currently working on and
if he carefully checked the else
statement the if-else statement in the
calculated high score position let's
come down have a look there,
let's scroll that down
so down here starting from 165 so
firstly the first part of the condition
is checking to see up here this first
one if the players score is greater than
equal to 1000 and if that's false then
obviously score isn't greater than 1000
so in other words when the first
condition is false what that means is
the score is less than 1000, so we get to
anywhere past that if that's true these
scores down here we know for a fact that
they aren't greater than 1000 because we
return false there but note that
in the second if, we're checking over
here to see whether the score player
score is less than 1000 but again if we
managed to get to this line we know
already that the player score is less
than 1000, otherwise we wouldn't have got
to that line, so the bottom line here is
that we can remove that condition since
it's always true, in other words because
the condition before this one at the top
we've already established that the
player score greater than equal to 1000
was false, this code here in other
words and if you've got the latest
intellij if you hover over here it will
actually tell you condition they're
players called less than thousand is
always true when reached, so in other
words when we get to this line again the
condition is already true, so there's no
reason to check that condition again, so
what we should do is remove that and the
same goes for the second condition there
we've got the same problem there because
we're checking to see whether the score
is greater than equal to 500 here and we
only get to this grid of group of code
if we if we know that the players score
is less than 500, so it's telling us
that's a redundant bit of code as well
so I'm going to remove both those paths
up to and including the n % the two
ampersands for the end and delete that
as well and if we actually run this up
now, you can see we've still got the same
results than what we got in the last
video, the bottom line is we don't have
to check the extra condition again since
that condition will always be true when
it reached that line of code but keep in
mind that this challenge can be written
in many different ways, you don't have to
match every single line with my solution
but it should work the same as per the
challenge text and you should get the
same results in other words and you can
also remove the else statement
have a return after the closing curly
brace the code would behave the same in
that scenario, so let's do that just to
be consistent there at the moment we've
got this else code here, so what we could
do instead we could actually remove that
you could just delete that code the
easiest way to do that would be just to
delete the else there and delete this
extra code brace, let's put that down
there like so so basically now we
haven't got another else so if those
three conditions end up being false it
drops down to here then we're just going
to return for anyway, just to make sure
that we'll run it to make sure we've got
the same results and you can see we've
still got the same results showing.
Alright, now before I end the video I want
to show you one more solution that
actually eliminates multiple return
statements, multiple return statements can
be confusing for people starting out in
a programming language, so let's instead
make our code easy to follow and use
only one return statement, so we're going
to do to achieve that is I'm going to
start by commenting out the code here
all this code up to and including the
return for comment that out and what we
can do instead of having these multiple
return statements that were their return 1
return 2, return 3 and return 4, we're
going to assume it or return 4 so what
we can do is by starting the code I'm
going to come down here and start typing
and into an int position equals 4 to
start out with and we're doing that
because we're assuming position 4 will
be returned and then what we're going to
do you're going to come down the next
time we're going to put if parentheses
player score is greater than equal to
100, we're going to type in code block
position equals 1 and you can probably
guess now hopefully what I'm going to do
with the rest of the code, I'm going to
put else if parentheses players score is
greater than equal to 500 and open a
code block position equals 2, we're gonna
put another else there the office is
gonna be else if
parentheses player score is greater than
equal to 100 open a code block put
position equals 3 then the last
statement we now need to add is the
return statement that actually returns
the value but instead of typing a fixed
number we're going to type return
position because I've already calculated
the position to be either the values 1 2
3 or 4 depending on the players score.
So let's actually run this and as you
can see again, we've got the same results
here but with different code and that's
us confirming the fact that there's
always almost always multiple ways to
solve a particular challenge and to code
a particular method in Java or in any
programming language, so what's actually
happening here with this code that we've
written is that we've got a variable
that we've set based on the condition
and we're returning the value of the
position variable, so therefore we've
only got one return statement instead of
having forward turn statements as we did
and then they'll commented out code, so
many developers find this easy to read
and follow and certainly outside for
beginners it is most likely easier
because there's only one return
statement to think about, so at the
beginning of our method calculate high
score position on line 76, we're setting
position to 4 and that's because if none
of their conditions are true in our
testing, but the codes on lines 78
through 84 then the 4 is going to be
returned because we initially set it to
4 and the position variable wasn't
changed in value, so based on the
condition variable, we'll get a different
value and then that value will be
returned with the code on line 86,
so basically in case the score the player's
score is greater than equal to 1000
positions set to 1 if the player score
is greater than equal to 500 it's going
to be set to 2 otherwise if the player
score is greater than equal to 100
the musicians 3 and of course we've
determined on line 76 that position was
4 initially so that will be the default
so if all three of these conditions end
up being false, the position will stay
with the value of 4 and then that will
be returned. Alright so that's a sum
like a bug fix and an alternative way to
do things and again I just really want
to make it very clear that there are
multiple ways to saw
of problems in computing so don't be too
were concerned if your code looks
different to mine the main thing is that
when you run it, it performs the same it
gets the same results that's really the
key thing here and as I'm showing you
that there are certainly many ways to
solve a particular problem. Alright, so
that's methods I hope you've got a lot
out of it. I'll see you in the next video.