it is tim buchalka here again I'd like
to thank you for your investment in this
course i'm going to do absolutely
everything in my power to help you get
up to speed to become a great java
programming programmers I should say as
quickly as possible before you get started
the code theirs a few very important things
that just wanna go through with you look
they'll only take a few minutes so
please bear with me
this will help you really
maximize your experience getting the
most out of this course
firstly high-definition content and this
video player does allow you to play
videos in different resolutions so what
you want to do is make sure you've
chosen the highest available resolution
via the gear icon which you can see
in the bottom right-hand corner of the
screen and essentially the higher the
number the better the quality now we'll
play up to 1080p videos so 1080p is the
quality of video that I've uploaded for
every video in this course the dates and if the
video to look low quality to you you
want to check while the video is playing and
make sure that you click on the gear icon
and make sure you have selected the
highest quality and do note that
depending on your internet speed the 1080p
option may not be available to 1080p
if you want to changed the speed of a video
in other words how fast it plays you can do
that by hovering over the 1x icon
as you can see on the screen they're
choosing a speed you want here is a close
up of that
now all videos have got close
captions on them to enable closed captions just
hover your mouse over the captions icon that
you can see pointing to the screen
there and click on English us that turns
the captions on
and once you've selected closed captions
on a single video all other videos in
the course will play with captions on
until you turn off that option so one of
the things you may need to do from time
to time is search for specific lecture
I do recommend that you start this
course in order and go to each
video in order but it can be a good
idea sometimes to do a search and
you can see that the main course
dashboard the course content tab has
got a lecture search box and in that box
you can actually type in a keyword or
different words you're looking for and
udemy will display a list of all the
lectures in these course that have those
words in the title for example you could
do a search for jdk and all the videos
in this course with lecture with that word
in the title will appear for you just an easy way to
find a particular lectures
now another very important thing for
programmers is to be able to search for
questions and answers you can do that by
going to the Q&A tab in udemy and once
you click on that you'll see that
there's a search box
and from there you can type in a
question or some keywords and
udemy will automatically find previous
questions and answers have been ask
that a similar to what you're searching for
so can be a good way just to find some
information immediately and then you
just click on the thread to read the
questions and all the answers that were
made for that particular post
if you can't find answers to your question
bearing in mind there are thousands
of questions and answers in the course so
it is definitely worth while you researching
first but if you can't find an answer you
can create a new question by clicking on
the ask a new question button just note
there that sometimes you may have to type
something in the box to the left before
the button becomes active enabled to
enable you to actually click it
so after pressing that button you'll be
taken to the question editor where you can
edit your question and post information
the question that your looking to get answered
a quick note a screenshot is
often recommended now rather than just
sort of saying that you got an error it
can often be really helpful to create a
screenshot of the problem on your screen and
using the mechanism that I got on the screen
here to upload that screenshot directly
to udemy
it's going to prompt you to drag and
drop an image or click it on the or
click on the choose file button once you
do that you can add the image to your
questions and the images will appear in
the Box similar to like you can see
there so you put the cursor where you
want the image to appear and i'll put
in it for you automatically
another really cool thing you can do is
you can also directly paste source code
into your question by just copying the
source code from your editor and pasting it
right in the box once you do that it
will show the source box in a box similar
to what you can see on the screen until your
questions actually save or posted and
once you do that you'll actually see
here that actually formats the code
and also nicely color codes as well so
this could be a really good way to
show the code that you're working on
and perhaps any errors so that myself or
other students can help you with
once you completed entering your question just
click on the post question button and
your questions are then posted to the course
and i actually get notified but also
other students will be able to see that and
chime in and answer it
one other thing I recommend you
do is when your question has been
solved by either myself or another student or
even yourself for that matter
it's a great idea to mark it as solved so
put two left square bracket and the word
solved into the title so this shows up in
the future searches and help other
students looking for help on that topic
because you know if you can see the
word solved you know that has
been a resolution to that problem and
directs people to that specific answer so
to do its quite simple you can edit
your question title and contents by
clicking on the question and then
clicking those three vertical dots you
can see to the top right of the image and
clicking on edit after clicking on edit
you now are able to edit the title and
content for that matter of your question
so you can now add the solved term on the
question title to mark it as solved and
once you've done that click on the save'
button once you done that that the question is
then updated you can see the title is
updated with the word solved in
square brackets
now something that you may want is the
source code so every single lecture in
this course has got its own source code
and also other resources such as links
etc that have been discussed in that
lecture now you will know that a lecture has
got resources because when you're
playing it and you move your mouse you
can see in the top left of the video
a little blue box
click on that box that opens up the
resources and from their you can click on to
download the source code or get access
to the various links if there are any
for that specific lecture
alternatively you can actually go down
to the bottom of the course in the source
code for all programs lecture which is in
the extra section and from there you can
also download the source code if you
want
and finally you find course news in the
announcement tab can be a good idea
to a click on that and check that
section out it will just keep you updated
on what's happening with this course you
should also get an email from me every
time that I do post an announcement
that's just another way for you to get
access to it
alright so that's all I wanted to say
about that let's now get cracking into
downloading and installing the necessary
tools so that we can start our java
programming see you in the next video